<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-24T17:14:46-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nishanth J. Kumar</title><subtitle>My personal homepage and blog for non-fictional musings</subtitle><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">A Beginner&amp;#8217;s Guide To Creating An Open Source Python Package</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/A-Beginner's-Guide-To-Creating-An-Open-Source-Python-Package/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Beginner's Guide To Creating An Open Source Python Package" /><published>2022-02-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/A-Beginner's-Guide-To-Creating-An-Open-Source-Python-Package</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/A-Beginner's-Guide-To-Creating-An-Open-Source-Python-Package/">&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I had the opportunity to develop and release a new open-source Python library: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vicariousinc/PGMax&quot;&gt;PGMax&lt;/a&gt;. Since this was to be my first open-source library release, I spent a lot of time figuring out a good set of developer tools to speed up development and enable (hopefully) lots of people to use and contribute to the project in the future. While there are already &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/build-your-first-open-source-python-project-53471c9942a7&quot;&gt;so&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://d39l7znklsxxzt.cloudfront.net/zh/blog/2021/01/19/publishing-a-proprietary-python-package-on-pypi-using-poetry/&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinmcbride.org/post/2021/creating-python-oss-project/&quot;&gt;different&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/free-code-camp/from-a-python-project-to-an-open-source-package-an-a-to-z-guide-c34cb7139a22&quot;&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt;, blog posts and resources on setting up open-source Python packages, none of them really presented a good integrated suite of tools for the various pieces (dependency management, documentation generation, continuous integration, etc.) that a well-engineered open-source project might want. So, I thought I would describe PGMax’s setup in the hopes that it might help others interested in setting up their own open-source library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I dive into describing all the packages and tools I used, I want to mention 2 things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This article assumes you’re planning to use GitHub to host your project’s repository. A lot of the tools used should integrate well with some other version control setup, but might not because it wasn’t written with any other setup in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of different tools and libraries covered in this post, and quite a few of them might be overkill for your needs. Feel free to pick and choose specific pieces based on your use-case!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dependency-management-and-packaging-with-poetry&quot;&gt;Dependency Management and Packaging with poetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every useful Python package relies on a plethora of other, existing Python packages. While there are many popular tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/pip/&quot;&gt;pip&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.conda.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;conda&lt;/a&gt; that help manage and maintain all the various packages and dependencies you might need to prevent the dreaded &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ImportError&lt;/code&gt;, most of these are intended for personal use and don’t seamlessly support all the needs that arise when building an open-source package that will (hopefully) be used and contributed to by hundreds of people. This is where &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/&quot;&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt; comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poetry is an easy-to-install tool that seamlessly handles pretty much all the use-cases you might have with developing an open-source package. It also has an intuitive CLI and some nice bells and whistles (one of my favorite: you can specify separate dependencies for developers and users and use these to make separate &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;virtualenvs&lt;/code&gt;!). Head over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/docs/#installation&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; and follow the instructions to install and setup poetry. Then, look under the “Project Setup” heading at &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/docs/basic-usage/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; to generate a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyproject.toml&lt;/code&gt; file which poetry treats as a one-stop-shop to manage your project. You can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/docs/basic-usage/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; to understand all the basic usecases, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/docs/cli/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; to see everything you can do with the CLI, but the general idea of how to use poetry is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Activate your poetry environment for development with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry shell&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whenever you want to add a new dependency/import a new library as part of development, do &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry add -D &amp;lt;library-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. If this will be needed for project users (not just developers) as well, simply do &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry add &amp;lt;library-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (you can also optionally specify particular versions of requirements, and even the source from which to get a specific library).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone else wants to start developing and contributing to your project, they can simply download the project repository and run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry shell&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry install&lt;/code&gt;, and they should have a nice, clean &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; with everything needed to run and develop the code (ta-da!).
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If someone just wants to use your package and isn’t interested in developing, they can run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry shell&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry install --no-dev&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;publishing-your-poetry-package-to-pypi&quot;&gt;Publishing your poetry package to PyPI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Poetry’s nicest features is its ability to easily publish packages to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/&quot;&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; so users can install the package painlessly with a simple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install &amp;lt;package_name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Before actually publishing your package though, it’s probably a good idea to test that it builds correctly and will upload to PyPI seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;testing-your-package-build-and-upload-with-test-pypi&quot;&gt;Testing your package build and upload with Test PyPI&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you haven’t already, add some miscellaneous, relevant fields to your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyproject.toml&lt;/code&gt; file. Such nice-to-have fields might include a license, a list of package authors and maintainers, a link to a homepage website, etc. You can see the full list of possible fields &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/docs/pyproject/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; and as a sample, PGMax’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyproject.toml&lt;/code&gt; file can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vicariousinc/PGMax/blob/master/pyproject.toml&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also, if you haven’t already, make an account on &lt;a href=&quot;https://test.pypi.org/&quot;&gt;Test PyPI&lt;/a&gt;. Note that this will be entirely separate from any PyPI account you may have registered for with the same username.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go ahead and build your package with the command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry build&lt;/code&gt;. This should create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt; folder with a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.whl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; file. Note that it’s probably a good idea to add this &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt; folder to your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to install this &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.whl&lt;/code&gt; file in a fresh environment (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://conda.io/projects/conda/en/latest/user-guide/tasks/manage-environments.html&quot;&gt;create a new Conda environment&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/3/library/venv.html&quot;&gt;venv&lt;/a&gt;) with the command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install dist/&amp;lt;name_of_.whl_file&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. If there are any dependency/other issues with this install, fix them now.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If your package has any tests/example code, try to run these to verify that the install really worked.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add Test PyPI as an alternate package repository to publish to: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry config repositories.testpypi https://test.pypi.org/legacy/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now, publish your package to Test PyPI: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry publish -r testpypi&lt;/code&gt;. You will need your account credentials for this. If there are any dependency errors, etc. with this resolve them now.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To verify that the upload looks good and works as intended, you can view it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://test.pypi.org/&quot;&gt;Test PyPI&lt;/a&gt; and then additionally try to install it in a fresh environment with the command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install --index-url https://test.pypi.org/simple/ --extra-index-url https://pypi.org/simple &amp;lt;your_package_name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/34514703/pip-install-from-pypi-works-but-from-testpypi-fails-cannot-find-requirements&quot;&gt;this StackOverflow answer&lt;/a&gt; if you’re curious about what this command does.)
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Again, run any test/example code to verify that this install is all good.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this works, then congrats! You’re now ready to upload your package to PyPI and can be assured that everything will work seamlessly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;uploading-your-package-to-pypi&quot;&gt;Uploading your package to PyPI&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you haven’t already, then &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/account/register/&quot;&gt;register for a PyPI account&lt;/a&gt;. Note that this is entirely separate from any account you may have on Test PyPI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publish your package with a simple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry publish&lt;/code&gt; command. You will need your PyPI account credentials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ta-da! Now you have a shiny new package on PyPI, ready for anyone to install with a simple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install &amp;lt;package-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; command!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;code-formatting-linting-and-other-nice-to-haves&quot;&gt;Code Formatting, Linting and other nice-to-haves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these things are relatively minor, they can save you (and people who want to use your project) from significant headaches in the future. Since these things are straightforward to setup and become increasingly important as your project grows, I recommend setting them up right at the outset. Specifically, I recommend using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://black.readthedocs.io/en/stable/&quot;&gt;black&lt;/a&gt; for code formatting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pycqa.github.io/isort/&quot;&gt;isort&lt;/a&gt; to sort imports and make sure they’re always in the same order (this is extremely useful when reviewing changes on GitHub)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flake8.pycqa.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;flake8&lt;/a&gt; for linting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mypy.readthedocs.io/en/stable/&quot;&gt;mypy&lt;/a&gt; for type-checking all your code. This might be somewhat annoying during development, but is useful to keep-around because it can help catch some extremely subtle type bugs (plus, you can make it ignore files/functions/lines you don’t want it to look at).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enforcing-code-formatting-with-pre-commit-hooks&quot;&gt;Enforcing Code Formatting with pre-commit hooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it can be somewhat painful to install and use all these formatting and type-checking tools together. Fortunately, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pre-commit.com/&quot;&gt;pre-commit&lt;/a&gt; tool can bundle and run all of these tools (and more) for you! What’s more, you can set this up to run whenever a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt; command is executed. To do this, simply:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install pre-commit by following &lt;a href=&quot;https://pre-commit.com/#installation&quot;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you’re using poetry (which I hope you are!) be sure to add &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt; as a developer dependency and do this installation (preferably via pip) &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; your poetry shell. You can accomplish all of this by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry add -D pre-commit&lt;/code&gt; after having activated your poetry env with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry shell&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Verify your installation by checking whether the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit --version&lt;/code&gt; command runs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file to specify the tools you want &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt; to run
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can have the terminal spit out a sample &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt; using the command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit sample-config&lt;/code&gt;. Copy pase the output of this command into &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you want you’d like to use all the nice tools specified above (black, isort, flake8 and mypy), copy paste the below into your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; repos:
 -   repo: https://github.com/PyCQA/isort
     rev: 5.8.0
     hooks:
     -   id: isort

 -   repo: https://github.com/ambv/black
     rev:  21.6b0
     hooks:
     -   id: black
         language_version: python3.7

 -   repo: https://github.com/pre-commit/pre-commit-hooks
     rev: v4.0.1
     hooks:
     -   id: check-added-large-files
         args: ['--maxkb=5120']
     -   id: trailing-whitespace
         files: (\.py|\.rst|\.yaml|)$
     -   id: check-merge-conflict

 -   repo: https://gitlab.com/pycqa/flake8
     rev: 3.9.2
     hooks:
     -   id: flake8
         # To turn this into an error, remove --exit-zero below
         args: ['--config', '.flake8.config','--exit-zero']
         verbose: true

 -   repo: https://github.com/pre-commit/mirrors-mypy
     rev: 'v0.902'  # Use the sha / tag you want to point at
     hooks:
     -   id: mypy
         additional_dependencies: [tokenize-rt==3.2.0]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Setup &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt; to run whenever you commit to GitHub by running the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit install&lt;/code&gt; command
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;If you’re using poetry, be sure to run this command within your poetry shell. Alternatively, you can run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry run pre-commit install&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Optional) Integrate &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt; with your IDE so you can run these checks for any file on save, etc. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=MarkLarah.pre-commit-vscode&quot;&gt;VSCode extension&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/9278-pre-commit-hook-plugin&quot;&gt;IntelliJ Plugin&lt;/a&gt;)
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You can also just run the command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre-commit run --files &amp;lt;path-to-your-files&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to selectively run these tools on specific files. If you’re like me and don’t enjoy typing all this out, you can make a bash alias by adding the below lines to the end of your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; pc ()
 {
     pre-commit run --files &quot;$1&quot;
 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Now, you can simply run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pc &amp;lt;path-to-yourfile&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;managing-jupyter-notebooks-with-jupytext&quot;&gt;Managing Jupyter Notebooks with jupytext&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jupyter Notebooks are better than plain old Python scripts for a variety of different purposes. Unfortunately, version control isn’t one of them. Keeping Jupyter Notebooks as part of your project can make code review and management an absolute nightmare. Fortunately, there is a solution: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mwouts/jupytext&quot;&gt;Jupytext&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jupytext essentially creates a text version of your notebook and updates this version whenever you update the notebook (or vice-versa, so you can edit your notebook just by editing the jupytext-produced text file!). This way, you can just commit these text files (that are amenable to version control) to your repo and then generate + edit the corresponding Jupyter notebooks if and when they’re needed. Here’s how to integrate Jupytext into your repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.ipynb&lt;/code&gt; to your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file within your GitHub repo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install Jupytext by following the instructions from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mwouts/jupytext#install&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you’re using poetry (which I hope you are!) be sure to add jupytext as a developer dependency and do this installation (preferably via pip) &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; your poetry shell!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pair all your notebooks with a file in text format by following the instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mwouts/jupytext#paired-notebooks&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! Be sure to commit the paired text files to GitHub’s version control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;testing-with-pytest&quot;&gt;Testing with pytest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a good test suite is absolutely essential for any open-source library that expects to be widely adopted and improve with time. As of this writing, pytest is arguably the most popular choice for a python testing library because of its ease-of-use coupled with exhaustive features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing and setting up PyTest is super easy: simmply follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.pytest.org/en/6.2.x/getting-started.html#install-pytest&quot;&gt;steps from the official documentation&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re using Poetry (which I hope you are!), make pytest a dependency of your project and install it within your poetry environment by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;poetry add pytest&lt;/code&gt; within your poetry shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re now ready to begin writing tests! To get started, follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.pytest.org/en/6.2.x/getting-started.html#install-pytest&quot;&gt;guide from the official documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you’re thinking about how to structure and organize your tests, I’d highly recommend checking out &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.pytest.org/en/6.2.x/goodpractices.html&quot;&gt;this set of best practices&lt;/a&gt;. Ensuring that your tests follow as many of these pointers as is reasonable will save you a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of headache down the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generating-documentation-with-sphinx&quot;&gt;Generating documentation with Sphinx&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever experienced the abject horror of having to make changes to a sprawling codebase with no comments or documentation &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; when everyone that’s worked on it is unavailable, you understand why documentation is important. Now of course, there’s a reason most people don’t like writing documentation: it’s an annoying overhead (especially when you’re just starting to work on your project). Fortunately, there are tools to make writing and maintaining documentation significantly &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; annoying (and even quite a delight). Enter Sphinx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/index.html&quot;&gt;Sphinx&lt;/a&gt; helps you turn documentation files into a beautiful website that makes it easy for users to navigate through your (potentially massive and sprawling) codebase and understand how different pieces work. What’s more, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/index.html&quot;&gt;Read the Docs&lt;/a&gt; hosts this website (generally for FREE!) and can be configured to update it whenever you push changes to your repo on GitHub. This way, your documentation is always up-to-date, and accessible to anyone on the Internet (which makes it &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more likely that people will want to use and help improve your library!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as of this writing, Sphinx can be a bit annoying and tricky to setup well, especially if you’d like to do non-default things to make your documentation look better. There are &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of different ways to configure Sphinx to build a great-looking website; I’ll describe the one I settled on for PGMax, which was inspired by the structure and setup of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jax.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;JAX documentation&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, this setup generates a separate page in the documentation for every function, class and exception in your codebase (which looks much nicer than cramming everything into a few pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-docstrings&quot;&gt;Writing DocStrings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Sphinx to actually do it’s magic, your code needs to have ‘docstrings’. If you haven’t heard of these before, the name is fairly self-explanatory: they’re strings placed throughout the codebase that document everything from a general description of each class to the input/output of a specific function. Docstrings have a specific structure and style to make them easily parseable, and there are 2 major styles to choose from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sphinxcontrib-napoleon.readthedocs.io/en/latest/example_google.html&quot;&gt;the Google Style&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://sphinxcontrib-napoleon.readthedocs.io/en/latest/example_numpy.html#example-numpy&quot;&gt;the NumPy Style&lt;/a&gt;. PGMax chose to go the Google route, but there’s no significant reason to choose one over the other. Whatever you do choose, make sure to write docstrings for all applicable parts of your code!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configuring-sphinx&quot;&gt;Configuring Sphinx&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started, follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/intro/getting-started-with-sphinx.html#quick-start&quot;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt; to install Sphinx and walk through a setup process to create a documentation folder for you project. PGMax uses the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sphinx-rtd-theme.readthedocs.io/en/stable/installing.html&quot;&gt;readthedocs theme&lt;/a&gt; to format documentation, so I’d certainly recommend installing this as well. Once you’ve completed this, follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/a/62613202/12014259&quot;&gt;this StackOverflow answer&lt;/a&gt; to setup your repo to use the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;autosummary&lt;/code&gt; directive correctly (which generates separate pages for each module in your documentation). Feel free to look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vicariousinc/PGMax/tree/master/docs&quot;&gt;PGMax’s documentation folder&lt;/a&gt; for reference. If all is now setup correctly, then if you navigate to your project’s documentation folder and run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;make html&lt;/code&gt; command, you should see a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; directory get created containing html pages with your documentation. If you open these pages with your browser, you should be able to view what your documentation pages look like! Be sure to click through most if not all of you pages to make sure everything has been generated correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-up-read-the-docs-with-github-integration&quot;&gt;Setting up Read the Docs with GitHub Integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have Sphinx building your documentation correctly locally, you can make your own website on &lt;a href=&quot;https://readthedocs.org/&quot;&gt;readthedocs.io&lt;/a&gt; to host and continuously update your documentation so any users can easily access it. To do this, simply follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/tutorial/index.html#sign-up-for-read-the-docs&quot;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt; (though adapted to your project instead of their tutorial example). Importantly, this integration should automatically update the documentation upon new pull-requests, so all you need to do whenever you update code and documentation is simply make a PR!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automating-things-with-continuous-integration-via-github-actions&quot;&gt;Automating things with Continuous Integration via GitHub Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve setup everything up till this point, then you should have a nice development environment and workflow ready-to-go. This is great, but there’s one subtle problem: what if you (or someone contributing to your open-source project) mess up? Suppose for example that you forget to run your pre-commit hooks before pushing to GitHub, or even worse, you forget to run all your tests with PyTest before a major change. There’s currently nothing that prevents you from doing any of these things, and while some of them (like forgetting to lint) might not matter as much, other slip-ups (like forgetting to test and thereby accidentally breaking things) could be extremely annoying and even costly to fix. Enter GitHub Actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/actions/learn-github-actions/introduction-to-github-actions&quot;&gt;GitHub Actions&lt;/a&gt; essentially allow you to do various things (run tests, lint, publish the package, etc.) upon “triggers” like committing, pushing or opening a Pull Request (PR) on GitHub. There are &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sdras/awesome-actions&quot;&gt;useful, interesting and awesome GitHub Actions&lt;/a&gt; out there, but I’m going to try to keep things simple and focus on the ones that dovetail well with the tools described above. Specifically, whenever someone pushes a commit, an action should enforce all our pre-commit hooks on any changed code. And whenever someone opens a PR, various actions should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enforce all pre-commit hooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to install all the Poetry dependencies and make sure it works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run all tests with PyTest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test that all documentation can be generated, then publish this documentation after PR approval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, after a new “release” of the repo is made, we want to automatically publish this new version to PyPi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PGMax uses two different files within its &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.github/workflows&lt;/code&gt; folder: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vicariousinc/PGMax/blob/master/.github/workflows/ci.yaml&quot;&gt;ci.yaml&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vicariousinc/PGMax/blob/master/.github/workflows/publish.yaml&quot;&gt;publish.yaml&lt;/a&gt;. Our &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ci.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file specifies all the actions that are run on push and pull-request events, whereas the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;publish.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file specifies actions to be run when a new release is made. Both files are fairly simple and reading their comments along with some of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/actions/reference/workflow-syntax-for-github-actions&quot;&gt;official GitHub Actions docs&lt;/a&gt; should be sufficient to enable you to understand what each part of each file does (if that’s not the case, feel free to post a comment or shoot me a message and I’m happy to help clarify things!). The only piece of setup that’s needed to get these actions to run in any other repo is the creation of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/actions/reference/encrypted-secrets&quot;&gt;GitHub Secret&lt;/a&gt; that enables GitHub to access my PyPI account when it needs to publish a new release of the package. To do this, simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/help/#apitoken&quot;&gt;create an API token&lt;/a&gt; on PyPI and then &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/actions/reference/encrypted-secrets#creating-encrypted-secrets-for-a-repository&quot;&gt;crete a new GitHub Secret&lt;/a&gt; named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PYPI_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt; and paste your PyPI API token as the “value” of the secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to directly use PGMax’s YAML files for your own GitHub actions, or pick and choose specific sections adapted to your project’s needs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro Tip: To make your GitHub repo look super professional, you can add a shiny badge to your README to display the status of your tests, documentation builds, etc. To do this, follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/actions/managing-workflow-runs/adding-a-workflow-status-badge&quot;&gt;these steps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all folks! I hope these tips and links are helpful, and that you don’t have to spend as much time as I did on figuring out how to setup your shiny new open-source Python library. If you do end up using this guide for your open-source library, do let me know; I’m excited to see what you build!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">A while ago, I had the opportunity to develop and release a new open-source Python library: PGMax. Since this was to be my first open-source library release, I spent a lot of time figuring out a good set of developer tools to speed up development and enable (hopefully) lots of people to use and contribute to the project in the future. While there are already so many different articles, blog posts and resources on setting up open-source Python packages, none of them really presented a good integrated suite of tools for the various pieces (dependency management, documentation generation, continuous integration, etc.) that a well-engineered open-source project might want. So, I thought I would describe PGMax’s setup in the hopes that it might help others interested in setting up their own open-source library.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Phd Statement Of Purpose</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/My-PhD-Statement-of-Purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Phd Statement Of Purpose" /><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/My-PhD-Statement-of-Purpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/My-PhD-Statement-of-Purpose/">&lt;p&gt;Writing a good PhD SoP can be a daunting task. Fortunately, there are plenty of good posts out there about how to approach the writing process and what a good SoP looks like (in particular, I followed the structure laid out by &lt;a href=&quot;https://timdettmers.com/2018/11/26/phd-applications/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://timdettmers.com/&quot;&gt;Tim Dettmers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://h2r.cs.brown.edu/writing-a-research-statement-for-graduate-school-and-fellowships/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by my undergrad advisor &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Pd8-ju0AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Stefanie Tellex&lt;/a&gt;). When I was writing my own SoP, what I probably found most-helpful on top of the above-linked posts was reading SoP’s by students in related areas who had been successful with the PhD application process (in particular &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.nelsonliu.me/2020/11/11/phd-personal-statement/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.stanford.edu/~nfliu/&quot;&gt;Nelson Liu&lt;/a&gt;). Given how much I benefitted from these, I figured I’d try to give back and contribute to the genre. Below, you can read the SoP that helped me get admitted to MIT:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; 

&lt;a href=&quot;/misc_files/MIT_SoP.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;p style=&quot;font-size:20px&quot;&gt; PhD Statement of Purpose &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to give two pieces of advice to anyone writing an SoP, it’d be these: make it both &lt;em&gt;research-dense&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;skimmable&lt;/em&gt;. I think it’s useful to think of an SoP as an application for a research job instead of a college essay: it should focus almost exclusively on things directly relevant to your ability to do good research (namely, your past experience and your interest and ideas going forward). Relentlessly cut-out any fluff. This is especially important because people on PhD admissions committees often skim SoP’s quickly (often because of the sheer volume of applications received). For this reason, it’s also useful to optimize your essay for skimming: do things like having the first 1 or 2 sentences of each paragraph setup what the paragraph will be about, or italicizing/bolding important words/sentences, etc. You shouldn’t take this too far and make your writing too terse or lazy though; remember that eventually, Professors will carefully read your entire SoP!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck with writing and the overall grad school application process!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Resources" /><summary type="html">Writing a good PhD SoP can be a daunting task. Fortunately, there are plenty of good posts out there about how to approach the writing process and what a good SoP looks like (in particular, I followed the structure laid out by this post by Tim Dettmers and this post by my undergrad advisor Stefanie Tellex). When I was writing my own SoP, what I probably found most-helpful on top of the above-linked posts was reading SoP’s by students in related areas who had been successful with the PhD application process (in particular this one from Nelson Liu). Given how much I benefitted from these, I figured I’d try to give back and contribute to the genre. Below, you can read the SoP that helped me get admitted to MIT:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Beginner&amp;#8217;s Guide To Undergrad Cs Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/A-Beginner's-Guide-to-Undergrad-CS-Research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Beginner's Guide To Undergrad Cs Research" /><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/A-Beginner's-Guide-to-Undergrad-CS-Research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/A-Beginner's-Guide-to-Undergrad-CS-Research/">&lt;p&gt;Computer Science has become quite the popular field these days, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cra.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Generation-CS.pdf&quot;&gt;especially amongst undergraduates&lt;/a&gt;. As a result, there are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more CS-related resources now than there ever were before. There are tons of books, lecture videos, guides, articles, and even memes about everything from understanding difficult CS concepts for coursework, to ‘cracking’ technical interviews, to applying to CS grad school. However, one aspect of an undergrad CS education that often gets left a bit in the dark is research [1]. While most University undergrads are probably aware that undergrad research opportunities exist, a surprising amount don’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; know (1) what undergrad research entails, (2) why they should care/potentially try to get involved, and (3) how to actually get a research opportunity. This is unfortunate because there’s been an overwhelming recent interest from students in going to CS graduate school or pursuing research-related jobs in industry, which both increasingly require at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; undergrad research experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own case, at the start of my freshman year, I had a pretty good idea of what coursework I’d need to do to get a CS degree, and quickly found out the why and how of recruiting for various summer internships. However, I knew next-to-nothing about undergrad research. I didn’t know - for instance - that most Professors’ primary responsibility is to do research, that being a “researcher” is a legitimate career option, or that research experience is important for grad school applications. Fortunately for me, I stumbled into some incredible undergrad research opportunities by happy accident. Research changed my life; I loved (and still love!) it so much that I spent my senior year working to &lt;a href=&quot;http://ur.cs.brown.edu/about/&quot;&gt;promote undergrad research opportunities within Brown’s CS department&lt;/a&gt; so that more students get to take advantage of the opportunities I’d gotten. One of the most common things I heard from students and peers is that they wished they had known more about research and gotten involved sooner. This post is an attempt to address that, as well as share some lessons I’ve learned as an undergrad researcher, by trying to answer three common, big-picture questions about undergrad research: what, why and how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- vscode-markdown-toc --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#WhattheheckisUndergradCSResearch&quot;&gt;What the heck is Undergrad CS Research?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#WhyshouldIcare&quot;&gt;Why should I care?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#HowshouldIgetinvolved&quot;&gt;How should I get involved?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Sometipsandadvice&quot;&gt;Some tips and advice&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#SomeDosandDontsofUndergradResearch&quot;&gt;Some Do’s and Dont’s of Undergrad Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#SomeImportantThingstoKeepinMind&quot;&gt;Some Important Things to Keep in Mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- vscode-markdown-toc-config
	numbering=true
	autoSave=true
	/vscode-markdown-toc-config --&gt;
&lt;!-- /vscode-markdown-toc --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-what-the-heck-is-undergrad-cs-research&quot;&gt;1. &lt;a name=&quot;WhattheheckisUndergradCSResearch&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What the heck is Undergrad CS Research?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CS research basically involves trying to push the boundaries of CS as a field and discover new knowledge about computers. If that sounds like a vague, fairly generic description, that’s because it is. One of the cool things about CS research is that it is really broad and hard to draw a precise box around. There are researchers working on everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-03348-4&quot;&gt;AI to predict protein folding&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/The_Limits_of_Quantum_Computers.pdf&quot;&gt;proving things quantum computers won’t be able to do&lt;/a&gt;. Pretty much every cool CS-related invention - from Object-Oriented Programming to web search and the protocols of the Internet - started out as a project in a research lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all well and good, but it says nothing about what &lt;em&gt;undergrad&lt;/em&gt; CS research involves. What does an undergrad researcher do on a daily basis? The answer is that, just like the content of CS research itself, it varies. However, there is some general structure in what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you join a lab as an undergrad, you’ll probably be mentored by a grad-student (generally, someone working towards their PhD) or post-doc (someone who’s finished their PhD) directly, with occasional meetings with one or more Professors. You’ll get to work on a project that’s directly related to one of the lab’s research directions in a very specific sub-field of CS. Especially in the beginning, you’ll likely spend a good amount of time reading academic papers and getting yourself acquainted with the lab’s work (which can take anywhere from a week to a few months). You may also be asked to work on a “starter project”, like implementing an existing paper or solving a problem-set from a related class, to get you up to speed and give you a taste of the kind of work you’ll be doing [2].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon enough, you’ll probably be tasked with working on some relatively well scoped-out part of an existing project. Most of the time, this means designing/implementing some code as part of a larger codebase, or implementing a novel algorithm someone on the project has come up with, or designing and running one or more experiments. More rarely (but common with theoretical CS research), you’ll be asked to help prove a theorem or do something else that’s rather math-heavy like derive the worst-case runtime of a new algorithm. Eventually, you might be asked to help write up the part you worked on as part of an academic paper. What’s common between these different tasks is that they’re usually fairly concrete: someone’s sketched out what needs to be done in broad strokes and your job is to figure out all the details of actually doing it. In this way, these aspects of research are not unlike what a traditional software engineer does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working on a few projects, you’ll probably have the opportunity to lead your own project, which will pretty-much simulate what being a grad student or professional researcher would be like. Unlike before, this will involve much less concrete things, like finding an interesting problem to work on and designing a completely novel solution for it. On a day-to-day basis, this will likely involve reading lots of papers (a core activity for a researcher at any stage of their career!), having research-related discussions with your mentors/advisors/collaborators and spending a significant amount of time just thinking. These aspects of research are rather significantly different from software engineering because there are no descriptions of what you need to produce, and it could very well be that &lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; has done something similar enough before. This means you’re not even really sure where to get started or what sort of tools/frameworks to use. Generally, if you find that you enjoy these rather unstructured, less-concrete parts of research, then it’s a pretty strong sign that you’ll enjoy being a researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from these technical aspects of actually doing your research, you’ll also likely spend time communicating your research by giving talks or poster presentations and attending conferences. However, these commitments are generally few and far between for undergrads when compared to the other aspects of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-why-should-i-care&quot;&gt;2. &lt;a name=&quot;WhyshouldIcare&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why should I care?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above description of CS research, hopefully it’s clear that research offers you the opportunity to (a) pursue an interest in a sub-topic of CS, and (b) learn a lot of interesting/useful skills/knowledge. This is great, but there are also so many other things - like working on a side-project, trying to start a startup, or doing web-dev for that cool new club - that you could do to reap similar benefits. Given this, here are a few benefits that are fairly unique to research:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is (probably) the best chance you’ll get to try it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, it’s exceptionally difficult to get involved with research if you’re not at a University. I’ve met quite a few people who became interested in research &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; graduation and their number one regret is that they didn’t take advantage of research opportunities while they were still doing their degree programs. In fact, gaining research experience is one of the most-common reasons that people decide to pursue Master’s degrees. Given that it’ll probably never be as easy to get involved with research as it is for you right now, you should probably at least give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll figure out if you want to be a researcher or not&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It’s possible to split all CS-related career paths you could possibly choose to pursue into 2 categories: research (becoming a research scientist, research engineer, professor, etc.) and not-research (software engineering, product management, consulting, tech entrepreneurship, etc.). The general rule I’ve been told by internship mentors, grad students and Professors is that it is much easier to switch from research to not-research than the other way around. Given this, and the point above, it’s incredibly useful to know if a research career is appealing to you or not. There’s no better way to figure this out for yourself than to get involved with research and seeing if you like it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll &lt;em&gt;massively&lt;/em&gt; strengthen grad-school applications (should you choose to apply)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Gaining research experience is probably the single best thing you can do to strengthen a grad school application (especially for PhD programs!) [3]. So if you’re at all considering going to grad school, getting involved with research is a very good thing to do. If you’re not sure about grad school (like most people are), then it’s still useful to get some research experience because it leaves that door open for you to decide later. It’s much better to have the experience and decide not to apply to grad school than to not have the experience and want to apply. Additionally, as mentioned above, doing undergrad research will essentially simulate what a PhD program program will be like, which will help you decide whether or not you’d even like to apply to grad school in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll get to form strong relationships with a Professor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Professors are generally extremely cool, intelligent and experienced people who can (and want to) be incredible mentors to your career and life. They can give you valuable advice on everything from what classes to take to how to think about what kind of person you want to be. They can also open doors to cool opportunities (internships, grad-schools, etc.) with strong letters of recommendation and/or connecting you with people they know in academia and industry (and most CS Professors know &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of interesting people!). In my own case, my undergrad research advisors are the best mentors I’ve had so far, and their advice changed my life and career trajectory; so I’d definitely &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommend getting to know your Professors better. While you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; do this through other avenues (TA’ing, going to a lot of their office hours, etc.) there’s nothing as direct as doing research with them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll strengthen job/internship applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Research projects - especially ones that are  relevant to roles you might be looking for - are appealing to potential employers. This is especially true if you’re interested in research-adjacent roles (e.g. “research intern”, “research engineer”, “machine learning engineer”, etc.). What’s more, letters of recommendation from a professor can open up opportunities that might not be otherwise available (both the industry internships I did during my undergrad years were roles that I was only able to interview for on recommendation from a Professor). Having said this, I want to make clear that doing research is &lt;em&gt;rarely&lt;/em&gt; the best use of your time if getting an industry internship/job is your primary goal; you’d be better off spending time on interview prep, side-projects, open-source contributions, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-how-should-i-get-involved&quot;&gt;3. &lt;a name=&quot;HowshouldIgetinvolved&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How should I get involved?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully at this point, you’re considering trying out this research thing for yourself. So how exactly do you go about getting involved? Fortunately, there are a lot of great existing articles and resources on this. Some posts I’ve found particularly helpful are &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@researchconnectcu/cornell-cs-research-readme-381206eaabcb&quot;&gt;this one from Cornell CS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.unc.edu/academics/undergraduate/how-to-undergraduate-research/&quot;&gt;this one from UNC Chapel Hill&lt;/a&gt;. While these articles include some school-specific information, the general process is roughly the same at any institution. Spend some time searching for information specific to your department and the various labs within it (if you happen to be a Brown student, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://ur.cs.brown.edu/&quot;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt; and get in touch with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ur.cs.brown.edu/about/&quot;&gt;MURA’s&lt;/a&gt;!). If you can’t seem to find much, then don’t hesitate to talk to/email a Professor directly. Overall, taking initiative and showing enthusiasm for research opportunities can go a long way towards getting them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what should you do if there aren’t that many relevant/exciting research opportunities within your school’s CS department? If you’re a citizen or permanent resident of the US, the NSF funds a “Research Experiences for Undergraduates” (REU) program with a bunch of exciting, paid research opportunities in a variety of different topics all across the world. You can find a list of these opportunities &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/crssprgm/reu/list_result.jsp?unitid=5049&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If this doesn’t apply to you, or none of these opportunities stand out to you, then I’d encourage you to try to find research opportunities through industry internships (e.g. an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dangkhoasdc/awesome-ai-residency&quot;&gt;AI Residency Program&lt;/a&gt;), virtual mentorships from established researchers (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.evjang.com/2020/06/free-office-hours-for-non-traditional.html&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;) or try cold-emailing professors or graduate students at nearby institutions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mtu.edu/biological/research/undergraduate/pdfs/mentor-email-guidelines.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; are some generally helpful guidelines for writing such an email that’s likely to get a response). If none of that works and you still have the urge to do research, then go for it and forge your own path. Read papers, try to come up with an idea, and start working on it! This will certainly be difficult, but no one is stopping you. Plenty of people (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://timdettmers.com/2020/03/10/how-to-pick-your-grad-school/&quot;&gt;Tim Dettmers&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://andreas-madsen.medium.com/becoming-an-independent-researcher-and-getting-published-in-iclr-with-spotlight-c93ef0b39b8b&quot;&gt;Andreas Madsen&lt;/a&gt;) have successfully pursued “independent” research (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mlcollective.org/&quot;&gt;there’s even an organization that helps foster this&lt;/a&gt;!). Again, I’d highly recommend taking initiative and showing enthusiasm: these are often the most important traits of a researcher and will significantly improve your chances of independent success or getting noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-some-tips-and-advice&quot;&gt;4. &lt;a name=&quot;Sometipsandadvice&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Some tips and advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve covered the basics of what, why, and how, let me share some tips and advice that I’ve gotten over the years and wish I’d known when I started as a bright-eyed bushy-tailed undergrad researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;41-some-dos-and-donts-of-undergrad-research&quot;&gt;4.1. &lt;a name=&quot;SomeDosandDontsofUndergradResearch&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Some Do’s and Dont’s of Undergrad Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work towards a paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you had to sum up a software engineer’s job in 3 words, “produce good code” would be a fairly apt description. If you had to do a similar thing for a researcher “produce good papers” would be it. Papers are the bread-and-butter of a researcher; pretty much all research projects aim to publish a paper in some capacity. Given this, if you want to get a true taste of what it’s like to be a researcher, you should work towards publishing a paper. Not doing so would be like trying to experience what it’s like to be a software engineer without working on a significant software project! By working towards a paper, you’ll not only get a real sampling of what it’d be like to be a professional researcher, but you’ll also have something tangible to show for it.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Now, to be clear, I’m not suggesting that you should only work on projects where you’ll be first-author on a paper that’s published at one of the top conferences or journals. I’m also not suggesting that you don’t work on projects whose outcome might &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be a traditional conference or journal paper - producing things like technical reports, posters or even deep-dive blog posts can often be just as useful of a learning experience as a traditional paper. It also takes time to practice and develop the various skills that go into good research, and it’s a good idea to start out by doing a small, unpublished starter project, or working on an existing codebase, or by joining a project led by someone more experienced. However, if you want to experience what research is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like (which you should!), you need to be part of at least one project that eventually publishes a paper (or something with similar qualities like a technical report, deep-dive blog post, poster, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you work on any other project (a code release for an existing paper, setting up infrastructure for experimentation, etc.), even if it’s within a research lab, be well-aware that what you’re experiencing isn’t fully representative of the research process, and that the fact that you enjoy this project doesn’t mean you’d enjoy being a professional researcher.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask for help and advice frequently&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Before I actually got involved with research, I imagined that researchers generally sat alone thinking about problems for long periods of time before having a “eureka” moment and writing some crazy important paper (a la Isaac Newton). I chuckled when I wrote that last sentence because this is actually pretty far from the truth: most research is extremely collaborative (notice how almost every paper you’ll read has more than one author). Sure, it’s sometimes useful to sit and think about a problem alone, but there’s no point banging your head against it repeatedly when you’re stuck: it’s not useful to you or anyone you might be working with.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid to ask for help and collaborate with others when you think they can help you get unstuck; discussing problems and brainstorming ideas can be one of the most enjoyable parts of research (it certainly is for me!).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set reasonable expectations with your advisor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Most undergrads feel the need to impress their advisor, especially when they first start out with research. As a result, it can be tempting to propose ridiculously hard-to-meet deadlines. Avoid doing this; the clearer you are about your time commitments, the easier it’ll be for your advisor to set expectations, and the more likely you’ll be to see your project through to completion instead of burning out and bowing out. Also, in general, it’s better to underpromise and overdeliver on deadlines than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dont’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flake&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This is unfortunately one of the most-common thing that happens with undergraduate researchers (and why some labs are hesitant to take any at all). Abandoning a research project suddenly and calling it quits is not only a letdown to the researchers you’re working with, but it also prevents you from getting a full taste of research and having something to show for it. Of course, if you truly can’t handle the workload, or actively hate what you’re working on, or aren’t getting enough time, help or guidance from the people you’re working with, then it can be a good idea to call it quits. However, undergrads often flake for simpler, more benign reasons: getting overwhelmed with other commitments and/or feeling stuck and not asking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Overall, I’d recommend that you stick with a research project to see it through, even if (more likely &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt;) it gets difficult, annoying or uninteresting, because some of the best parts come &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the worst ones. Also, sticking with a project will give you a true taste for the entire research process, and leave you with something to show for all your efforts at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feel too bad about not making much progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Research is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;, and this is especially true when you’re just starting out. One of the things that makes it so hard is that research progress if often highly non-linear. It’s possible (and somewhat common) to make very little progress on a project despite putting in effort. Projects also fail entirely from time to time. In this way, research is very much unlike course work or personal projects, and often much more frustrating for undergrads used to relatively linear payouts for work put in.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;However, it’s important to realize this &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; just happening to you: all researchers get stuck on problems and feel frustrated [4], but it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get better with time and experience. As an undergrad, you can try to mitigate the frustration that comes from a lack-of-progress by leaning on your mentors and collaborators more, focusing on what you can control (the time and effort you’re putting in), and even potentially joining multiple projects so that you can switch gears to another project whenever you’re feeling stuck. However, it’s also important to pay attention to your feelings: if you’re finding that you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t like the frustration of being stuck, and would much prefer to make more linear progress on your work, then that’s a strong and useful signal that you probably won’t be very happy as a researcher.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assume a Professor’s research is just like that course you took with them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;While Professors generally teach classes that are at least tangentially related to their research, this is not necessarily the case. Also, even if their research does cover the exact topic from a class you took with them, there is usually a big difference between learning material/doing class assignments and doing research. Try to do some of your own research on a lab’s recent work before trying to join it: skim some recent papers and maybe even go to a lab meeting (you’ll usually be welcome!). If you’d like to get a taste for the research process, see if your Professor teaches a seminar or graduate class related to their research and see if you can enroll in it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;42-some-important-things-to-keep-in-mind&quot;&gt;4.2. &lt;a name=&quot;SomeImportantThingstoKeepinMind&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Some Important Things to Keep in Mind&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s okay to feel like you don’t know what you’re doing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It’s easy to feel lost and overwhelmed when trying to do research, especially as an undergrad. This is okay. In fact, it’s normal and believe it or not, most senior researchers feel like they don’t know what they’re doing quite often. This isn’t too surprising when you really think about it: research &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; involves straying beyond the boundaries of the field into the unknown. If you know exactly what you’re doing all the time, you’re probably not exploring far enough. One of the most significant and sobering things my undergrad research advisor told me is that the feeling of not knowing what you’re doing doesn’t really ever go away, even as a Professor. The best researchers learn to accept this and operate well despite not truly knowing how exactly things will pan out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re probably not bothering/annoying them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Professors and grad students are often incredibly busy juggling a jaw-dropping number of tasks. As a result, it’s easy to feel like emailing them or asking for a meeting when you’re stuck/need help is bothersome and annoying. It’s usually not - especially if you’re blocked/stuck on something where a quick email/meeting could save you hours (and a significant amount of headache). That being said, it’s probably not a good idea to email out a cry for help for every problem you encounter without first trying to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In general, a good rule of thumb is that you should have exhausted all the &lt;em&gt;reasonable&lt;/em&gt; options you can think of for solving whatever problem you’re confronted with before asking for help. This will not only often help you resolve most problems/develop a better problem-solving intuition, but also will enable you to ask much better questions by describing what you’ve already done and your thoughts on why they didn’t work. An email saying “Stuck on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;problem x&lt;/code&gt; and have no clue what’s going on pls HALP!” is much less productive than one saying “I’ve tried solution attempt &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;a, b, and c&lt;/code&gt; to solve problem &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and this is what happened in each of the cases, any thoughts on how to proceed?”. If you’re looking for more detailed guidelines on when and how to ask good questions, check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/help/how-to-ask&quot;&gt;StackOverflow post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re a valuable asset to your research group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;As an undergrad, it’s easy to look at the incredibly smart and productive grad students and Professor(s) in your group and feel like your contributions aren’t particularly important or valuable to the group. While you might not be producing as much as a grad student or Professor, that certainly does not mean you aren’t valuable (if that were the case, then the group wouldn’t have hired you and wouldn’t be interested in keeping you around!). In fact, aside from their direct contributions to projects, undergrads can prove valuable in some non-obvious ways. For instance, having an interested undergrad ask basic questions about a project or paper can often force people who’ve been working on the project for a while to rethink some fundamental assumptions and ultimately come up with better ideas (I’ve seen this happen; never hesitate to ask basic questions!). Additionally, working with undergrads helps grad students/post-docs acquire valuable collaboration and mentorship skills, which are part of the reason they chose their jobs in the first place. All in all, your work and presence as an undergrad are often much more valuable than you realize.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being an undergrad and doing research is hard: it’s okay to ask for extensions/take some time off.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Being an undergrad means having a significant course load &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a bunch of external commitments to clubs, part-time jobs, etc. Research will always have to be done on top of all this, which is hard to say the least. There will be some weeks when all your commitments overwhelm you and make it hard to get much research work done. This is fine. Grad students and Professors understand this (all of them were once undergrads and many of them likely know what it’s like to be in your shoes). And more often than not, they’re more than willing to accommodate you if you need to push back some deadlines, etc. That being said, it’s useful to try to plan in advance, set reasonable deadlines and expectations for how much time you can commit to research in any given semester, and avoid over-promising.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Persistence goes a long way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Research is very much a skill and, like all other skills, takes time and practice to develop. Research also has a long learning curve: it’s difficult to ‘teach’ someone how to do good research with a couple lectures. Rather, ideas, concepts and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://joschu.net/blog/opinionated-guide-ml-research.html&quot;&gt;good taste for problems&lt;/a&gt; tend to sink in with experience over time. So don’t be surprised if you feel like you’re not getting much better at research in the beginning. If you choose to stay at it, you’ll find yourself improving slowly and rather unnoticeably to you, till some day you give a talk or mentor new undergrads yourself and realize how far you’ve come.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it! Hopefully that’s enough to give you an idea of what undergrad research is, why you might want to get involved and how to actually do it, plus some tips and advice that I wish I’d been given when I started out. I hope some of this has been informative, and even convinced you to give undergrad research a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck - I can’t wait to hear about what you build :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] As an example, the only substantive guide to undergrad research I’ve been able to find online is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/cv8o3t/iama_cs_researcher_let_me_tell_you_about/&quot;&gt;this Reddit AMA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] If you’re working on a starter project and get stuck, don’t hesitate to reach out to a lab member to ask for help! Contrary to what it might seem like, asking for help will usually be taken as a positive sign that you’re really interested in the work and excited to learn. Far too many undergrads give up after getting stuck on a starter project without even asking for help - so avoid this mistake if you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] See &lt;a href=&quot;https://timdettmers.com/2018/11/26/phd-applications/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://da-data.blogspot.com/2015/03/reflecting-on-cs-graduate-admissions.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~harchol/gradschooltalk.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2017-12-01/the-godfather-of-ai-was-almost-a-carpenter-video&quot;&gt;There’s a famous story&lt;/a&gt; about how Geoffrey Hinton - a “godfather” of AI, inventor of Deep Learning and giant in the field of CS as a whole - got so frustrated with not being able to come to a satisfying understanding of how the brain works as an undergrad that he gave up on science and research entirely to become a carpenter for a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://dsam99.github.io/&quot;&gt;Dylan Sam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cs.brown.edu/people/rpatel59/&quot;&gt;Roma Patel&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://qiuhongannawei.me/&quot;&gt;Anna Wei&lt;/a&gt; for providing comments and feedback on a draft of this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Resources" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Research" /><category term="Grad-School" /><summary type="html">Computer Science has become quite the popular field these days, especially amongst undergraduates. As a result, there are a lot more CS-related resources now than there ever were before. There are tons of books, lecture videos, guides, articles, and even memes about everything from understanding difficult CS concepts for coursework, to ‘cracking’ technical interviews, to applying to CS grad school. However, one aspect of an undergrad CS education that often gets left a bit in the dark is research [1]. While most University undergrads are probably aware that undergrad research opportunities exist, a surprising amount don’t really know (1) what undergrad research entails, (2) why they should care/potentially try to get involved, and (3) how to actually get a research opportunity. This is unfortunate because there’s been an overwhelming recent interest from students in going to CS graduate school or pursuing research-related jobs in industry, which both increasingly require at least some undergrad research experience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Strange Python List Multiplication Behavior</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Strange-Python-List-Multiplication-Behavior/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Strange Python List Multiplication Behavior" /><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Strange-Python-List-Multiplication-Behavior</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Strange-Python-List-Multiplication-Behavior/">&lt;p&gt;I recently spent on the order of 2 hours debugging some code that it only took me 1 hour to write. This post is partially intended to be informational for a reader and partially intended to serve as a future warning/reminder for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s suppose you want to create a new Python list and initialize it with all 0’s. Python provides a nice, intuitive and convenient way to do this with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; operator:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; my_list = [0] * 5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, and now you can edit/insert a value into any list index like you’d expect:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; my_list[0] = 23
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(my_list)
[23, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, suppose you want to kick it up a dimension and initialize a 2D list (i.e, a list of lists) with all 0’s. It’s only natural to use the nice and convenient &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; operator right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; my_2d_list = [[0] * 5] * 5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this doesn’t do what you intuitively think it does. To illustrate, let’s go and edit the top-left element&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; my_2d_list[0][0] = 1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(my_2d_list)
[[1, 0, 0, 0, 0], 
[1, 0, 0, 0, 0], 
[1, 0, 0, 0, 0], 
[1, 0, 0, 0, 0], 
[1, 0, 0, 0, 0]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how not just the top-left element, but &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; elements in the first column got edited to the same value! What gives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; operator to duplicate a list multiple times doesn’t create new lists, but just references the same underlying list object. This is almost &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; what someone wants when making a 2D (or multi-dimensional) list. But the behavior has to be this way for compatibility reasons (as explained in &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/240178/list-of-lists-changes-reflected-across-sublists-unexpectedly&quot;&gt;these nice StackOverflow answers&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t know about any of this before, don’t feel bad - I’d been using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; operator to make Python lists for ~5 years before this and somehow never realized this particular quirk…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in conclusion, &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; make a more-than-1D Python list with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; operator. If you want to be extra safe, stop using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; operator to make lists at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re here because you’re trying to debug strange Python behavior (hi future me!), and the quirk mentioned here wasn’t at the root of it, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/satwikkansal/wtfpython&quot;&gt;this GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; for an exhaustive illustration of Python’s weirdnesses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Resources" /><category term="Technical" /><summary type="html">I recently spent on the order of 2 hours debugging some code that it only took me 1 hour to write. This post is partially intended to be informational for a reader and partially intended to serve as a future warning/reminder for me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Nsf Grfp Application Materials</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/My-NSF-GRFP-Application-Materials/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Nsf Grfp Application Materials" /><published>2021-04-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/My-NSF-GRFP-Application-Materials</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/My-NSF-GRFP-Application-Materials/">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was incredibly excited and humbled to learn that I was selected as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsfgrfp.org/&quot;&gt;2021 NSF GRFP Fellow&lt;/a&gt;. Like most of my accomplishments, this one was only made possible by the support of friends and colleagues, and the mentorship of my incredible advisors at Brown. One resource I found particularly helpful for this application was previous successful applications, specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://vdean.github.io/&quot;&gt;Victoria Dean’s&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.nelsonliu.me/2020/10/13/nsf-grfp-materials/&quot;&gt;Nelson Liu’s&lt;/a&gt;. Given how useful these were for me, I figured I’d share my own application materials to contribute to the genre and help any future applicants. You can find both my research and personal essays linked below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; 

&lt;a href=&quot;/misc_files/GRFP_personal.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;p style=&quot;font-size:20px&quot;&gt; Personal Essay &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/misc_files/GRFP_research.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;p style=&quot;font-size:20px&quot;&gt; Research Essay &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one piece of advice I’d give to anyone applying for the GRFP, it’s this: share your materials with as many grad students, professors and other researchers you can! It’s often daunting to share personal or professional essays with others (and the GRFP requires both!), but feedback from more experienced researchers - especially those who might have either written or seen successful GRFP applications in the past - is absolutely invaluable. Of course, you don’t have to listen to incorporate &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; piece of feedback you get, but often, you’ll be surprised at the suggestions you’ll get and realize you can make your application much stronger by changing a few paragraphs, etc. (this certainly happened to me!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck with your GRFP applications!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Resources" /><summary type="html">Recently, I was incredibly excited and humbled to learn that I was selected as a 2021 NSF GRFP Fellow. Like most of my accomplishments, this one was only made possible by the support of friends and colleagues, and the mentorship of my incredible advisors at Brown. One resource I found particularly helpful for this application was previous successful applications, specifically Victoria Dean’s and Nelson Liu’s. Given how useful these were for me, I figured I’d share my own application materials to contribute to the genre and help any future applicants. You can find both my research and personal essays linked below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Featured On The Mit Admissions Blogs!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Featured-on-the-MIT-Admissions-Blogs!/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Featured On The Mit Admissions Blogs!" /><published>2021-04-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Featured-on-the-MIT-Admissions-Blogs!</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Featured-on-the-MIT-Admissions-Blogs!/">&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite blogs in the whole wide Internet is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitadmissions.org/blogs/&quot;&gt;MIT Admissions Blog&lt;/a&gt;. Admittedly, this used to be because I wanted nothing more than to become an MIT undergrad. However, I’ve continued to keep up with these blogs even after being rejected from MIT because many of the posts have been exceptionally genuine, relatable, and even insightful. In fact, I actually kept a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitadmissions.org/blogs/entry/50_things/&quot;&gt;one of my favorite advice posts&lt;/a&gt; pinned to my phone’s notes app throughout my time in college and it stayed relevant and insightful over all 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that my undergrad journey is coming to an end, I’ve been in a rather reflective mood. Recently, I spent some time reflecting on my journey from getting rejected as an undergrad applicant to MIT to now having committed to join the Ph.D. program in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.csail.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;CSAIL&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to write some of these thoughts up and email &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitadmissions.org/blogs/author/petey/&quot;&gt;Chris Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, who encouraged me to apply to MIT years ago. To my elation, he decided to share my story by publishing my email on the MIT Admissions Blogs! As someone who’s followed these blogs for close to 6 years now, having my own post up there is a huge personal milestone and dream come true. If someone had told me 4 years ago, when I was still trying to console myself after being rejected from MIT, that my college journey would turn out well enough to merit a post on the MIT blogs, I probably would have thought they were frothing-at-the-mouth crazy. Yet somehow, here we are, and I can’t help feel so incredibly lucky and grateful for how things have played out :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to be reading this and are currently feeling a bit disappointed or hopeless by a recent rejection or setback (hello future me!), I hope this story brings you some comfort, motivation or hope to keep persisting toward goals you care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the actual blog post on MIT Admissions’ site &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitadmissions.org/blogs/entry/denied-by-mit-now-a-phd-student-at-csail/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><category term="Resources" /><summary type="html">One of my favorite blogs in the whole wide Internet is the MIT Admissions Blog. Admittedly, this used to be because I wanted nothing more than to become an MIT undergrad. However, I’ve continued to keep up with these blogs even after being rejected from MIT because many of the posts have been exceptionally genuine, relatable, and even insightful. In fact, I actually kept a copy of one of my favorite advice posts pinned to my phone’s notes app throughout my time in college and it stayed relevant and insightful over all 4 years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Goldwater Application Sample</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/My-Goldwater-Application-Sample/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Goldwater Application Sample" /><published>2020-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/My-Goldwater-Application-Sample</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/My-Goldwater-Application-Sample/">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, I had the incredible privilege of being named a Goldwater Scholar. While winning the scholarship was rather validating and motivating, I thought the application process worthwhile in of itself because it forced me to think hard about my research direction and career goals for the future. During the application process, I found it incredibly helpful to read past sample applications. However, such samples are pretty few and far between, especially within the Computer Science or Mathematics categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, I thought I’d put my own application online in the hopes that future Goldwater applicants find it helpful. Below, you’ll find my responses to all the short essay questions + my research essay; which represent the bulk of the Goldwater application. If you’re reading this and considering applying to the Goldwater but currently on the fence, I’d highly recommend you try it (especially if you’re a sophomore because you can apply again next year!). If you’re in no way planning to apply for the scholarship but just reading this anyways, I hope it’s at least mildly interesting / entertaining…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In one or two sentences, describe your career goals and professional aspirations (see example below). This statement will be used in publications if you are selected as a scholar or honorable mention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obtain a PhD in Artificial Intelligence. Conduct research aiming to develop intelligence algorithms to enable practical and collaborative robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are your career goals and professional aspirations? Indicate which area(s) of mathematics, science or engineering you are considering pursuing in your research career and specify how your current academic program and your overall educational plans will assist you in achieving your career goals and professional aspirations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been dreaming of creating intelligent robots for many centuries now. Intelligent and collaborative robots could enable everything from creating an extraterrestrial habitat on Mars to making nuclear fusion reactors a viable source of clean and safe energy. The potential applications of these robots are so vast that it seems like their development could fundamentally change the world for the better, similar to how computers have changed our world by an unprecedented factor in only the last 50 years. The prospect of having widespread intelligent and collaborative machines at our disposal is thus exciting indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, my primary career goal is to accelerate the development of such intelligent and collaborative robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that creating such robots is not a simple task in the slightest. Such intelligent and collaborative robots have not even been created in a laboratory setting yet. Hence, it is clear to me that I need to spend time learning as much as I can about these fields and attempt to advance the state-of-the-art in research as much as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, I am pursuing an undergraduate degree in Computer Engineering. I believe that to create truly useful robots, we must make progress in creating increasingly intelligent algorithms in addition to cheaper, more accurate sensors and actuators. Thus, I see the challenges of robotics as fundamentally being challenges of computer science and engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to study computer engineering because it enables me to gain foundational knowledge in both fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of my curriculum, I am a member of a Robotics and Artificial Intelligence lab on campus. As a lab member, I am able to learn and work on independent research projects to advance the current state-of-the-art in various sub-fields like Planning, Reinforcement Learning, Imitation Learning and Human-Robot Interaction. I am also able to constantly learn about the field from my fellow researchers within the lab and around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduation, I intend to pursue a Ph.D. in Computer Science with a focus on artificial intelligence for robots. I want to build upon the foundation I will have laid to focus both on developing intelligence algorithms for robots and on creating interfaces to facilitate better human-robot collaboration. At the completion of my Ph.D., I hope to have made significant contributions to the state-of-the-art for robot learning and be well-equipped to help build the robots of our dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Describe an activity or experience that has been important in helping shape or reinforce your desire to pursue a research career in science, mathematics or engineering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first research internship involved helping a colleague with his project: using data from expert demonstrations to teach a robot how to press buttons. My colleague already had an algorithm; all that was left was to implement it on our lab’s mobile robot. We didn’t think this would take more than two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, we were very wrong. Our initial attempts resulted in our robot’s arm frequently hitting obstacles. Some weeks of debugging yielded a flaw in our algorithm. Some more weeks and extensive tests revealed our data-collection programs weren’t actually collecting data. Weeks continued to pass until my colleague graduated and we lost hope that the idea would work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, on the urging of an advisor, another colleague and I began re-examining the project. We ran meticulous experiments until we finally discovered a small error with our data collection. Days later, approximately one year after having gotten involved in the project, I held my breath and watched the robot press a button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While button-pressing may seem a trivial task, that moment was one of the most profound experiences of my life. Despite the many setbacks and frustrations, I continue with research to this day because such moments of discovery, of knowing that I have created something significant, novel and potentially impactful, have made everything else well worth it. Research is the most exciting and fulfilling pursuit I have ever known and I’m excited to spend the rest of my life doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Goldwater Scholars will be representative of the diverse economic, ethnic and occupational backgrounds of families in the United States. Describe any social and/or economic impacts you have encountered that influenced your education - either positively or negatively - and how you have dealt with them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in my father’s relatively small hometown in South India where opportunities were scarce. My high school had no guidance counselor and the nearest SAT Testing Center was a three-hour drive. However, my parents are both hard-working immigrants to the US who taught me to dream big and then persevere relentlessly for those dreams. So, I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I taught myself electronics and computer programming and began competing in national - and eventually international - robotics competitions and science fairs. I took a ninety-minute bus ride every day for six years to attend my city’s only international school. Eventually, I was able to achieve my dream of being accepted to study engineering at a research-driven college in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should emphasize that I’ve had the good fortune of being supported by great people throughout my journey thus far. My parents have never spared expenses on my education or pursuit of opportunity. My high school teachers nominated me for every relevant extracurricular opportunity they could and stayed after school hours to mentor me. My school’s chairman even fully-sponsored our Robotics team when costs became prohibitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experiences have taught me that it’s important to encourage and support students everywhere to pursue opportunity, no matter how scarce it may be. Sometimes, this support can change a life, as it did mine. In this spirit, I hope that my career and life can contribute to making the world have more opportunity for everyone, everywhere.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/misc_files/Goldwater_Research_Essay.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;p style=&quot;font-size:20px&quot;&gt; My Research Essay &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(PS: If you’re looking to write your Research Essay in LaTex, I’d highly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overleaf.com/latex/templates/goldwater-scholarship-research-essay-template/pmhbjqwgvdvb&quot;&gt;this free, open-source template&lt;/a&gt; by 2019 Goldwater Scholar Thomas Richards).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Resources" /><summary type="html">Earlier this year, I had the incredible privilege of being named a Goldwater Scholar. While winning the scholarship was rather validating and motivating, I thought the application process worthwhile in of itself because it forced me to think hard about my research direction and career goals for the future. During the application process, I found it incredibly helpful to read past sample applications. However, such samples are pretty few and far between, especially within the Computer Science or Mathematics categories. Given this, I thought I’d put my own application online in the hopes that future Goldwater applicants find it helpful. Below, you’ll find my responses to all the short essay questions + my research essay; which represent the bulk of the Goldwater application. If you’re reading this and considering applying to the Goldwater but currently on the fence, I’d highly recommend you try it (especially if you’re a sophomore because you can apply again next year!). If you’re in no way planning to apply for the scholarship but just reading this anyways, I hope it’s at least mildly interesting / entertaining… In one or two sentences, describe your career goals and professional aspirations (see example below). This statement will be used in publications if you are selected as a scholar or honorable mention. Obtain a PhD in Artificial Intelligence. Conduct research aiming to develop intelligence algorithms to enable practical and collaborative robots. What are your career goals and professional aspirations? Indicate which area(s) of mathematics, science or engineering you are considering pursuing in your research career and specify how your current academic program and your overall educational plans will assist you in achieving your career goals and professional aspirations. Humans have been dreaming of creating intelligent robots for many centuries now. Intelligent and collaborative robots could enable everything from creating an extraterrestrial habitat on Mars to making nuclear fusion reactors a viable source of clean and safe energy. The potential applications of these robots are so vast that it seems like their development could fundamentally change the world for the better, similar to how computers have changed our world by an unprecedented factor in only the last 50 years. The prospect of having widespread intelligent and collaborative machines at our disposal is thus exciting indeed. Given this, my primary career goal is to accelerate the development of such intelligent and collaborative robots. I recognize that creating such robots is not a simple task in the slightest. Such intelligent and collaborative robots have not even been created in a laboratory setting yet. Hence, it is clear to me that I need to spend time learning as much as I can about these fields and attempt to advance the state-of-the-art in research as much as I can. To this end, I am pursuing an undergraduate degree in Computer Engineering. I believe that to create truly useful robots, we must make progress in creating increasingly intelligent algorithms in addition to cheaper, more accurate sensors and actuators. Thus, I see the challenges of robotics as fundamentally being challenges of computer science and engineering. I chose to study computer engineering because it enables me to gain foundational knowledge in both fields. Outside of my curriculum, I am a member of a Robotics and Artificial Intelligence lab on campus. As a lab member, I am able to learn and work on independent research projects to advance the current state-of-the-art in various sub-fields like Planning, Reinforcement Learning, Imitation Learning and Human-Robot Interaction. I am also able to constantly learn about the field from my fellow researchers within the lab and around the world. After graduation, I intend to pursue a Ph.D. in Computer Science with a focus on artificial intelligence for robots. I want to build upon the foundation I will have laid to focus both on developing intelligence algorithms for robots and on creating interfaces to facilitate better human-robot collaboration. At the completion of my Ph.D., I hope to have made significant contributions to the state-of-the-art for robot learning and be well-equipped to help build the robots of our dreams. Describe an activity or experience that has been important in helping shape or reinforce your desire to pursue a research career in science, mathematics or engineering My first research internship involved helping a colleague with his project: using data from expert demonstrations to teach a robot how to press buttons. My colleague already had an algorithm; all that was left was to implement it on our lab’s mobile robot. We didn’t think this would take more than two months. As it turned out, we were very wrong. Our initial attempts resulted in our robot’s arm frequently hitting obstacles. Some weeks of debugging yielded a flaw in our algorithm. Some more weeks and extensive tests revealed our data-collection programs weren’t actually collecting data. Weeks continued to pass until my colleague graduated and we lost hope that the idea would work. However, on the urging of an advisor, another colleague and I began re-examining the project. We ran meticulous experiments until we finally discovered a small error with our data collection. Days later, approximately one year after having gotten involved in the project, I held my breath and watched the robot press a button. While button-pressing may seem a trivial task, that moment was one of the most profound experiences of my life. Despite the many setbacks and frustrations, I continue with research to this day because such moments of discovery, of knowing that I have created something significant, novel and potentially impactful, have made everything else well worth it. Research is the most exciting and fulfilling pursuit I have ever known and I’m excited to spend the rest of my life doing it. Goldwater Scholars will be representative of the diverse economic, ethnic and occupational backgrounds of families in the United States. Describe any social and/or economic impacts you have encountered that influenced your education - either positively or negatively - and how you have dealt with them. I grew up in my father’s relatively small hometown in South India where opportunities were scarce. My high school had no guidance counselor and the nearest SAT Testing Center was a three-hour drive. However, my parents are both hard-working immigrants to the US who taught me to dream big and then persevere relentlessly for those dreams. So, I did. I taught myself electronics and computer programming and began competing in national - and eventually international - robotics competitions and science fairs. I took a ninety-minute bus ride every day for six years to attend my city’s only international school. Eventually, I was able to achieve my dream of being accepted to study engineering at a research-driven college in the U.S. I should emphasize that I’ve had the good fortune of being supported by great people throughout my journey thus far. My parents have never spared expenses on my education or pursuit of opportunity. My high school teachers nominated me for every relevant extracurricular opportunity they could and stayed after school hours to mentor me. My school’s chairman even fully-sponsored our Robotics team when costs became prohibitive. My experiences have taught me that it’s important to encourage and support students everywhere to pursue opportunity, no matter how scarce it may be. Sometimes, this support can change a life, as it did mine. In this spirit, I hope that my career and life can contribute to making the world have more opportunity for everyone, everywhere. My Research Essay (PS: If you’re looking to write your Research Essay in LaTex, I’d highly recommend this free, open-source template by 2019 Goldwater Scholar Thomas Richards).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I Learned From 500 Days Of Meditation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/What-I-Learned-From-500-Days-Of-Meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I Learned From 500 Days Of Meditation" /><published>2020-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/What-I-Learned-From-500-Days-Of-Meditation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/What-I-Learned-From-500-Days-Of-Meditation/">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a screenshot from my profile page on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tenpercent.com/&quot;&gt;10% Happier&lt;/a&gt; guided meditation App:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/meditation-pics/screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;App Screenshot&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;It's been a lot of sitting-with-my-eyes-closed&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As of today, I’ve meditated for just over 500 days total with this app. My meditation habit actually started before getting the app, and I didn’t log a few days here and there, so overall I’ve probably been meditating somewhere around 600 days; averaging between 5 and 10 minutes each day. I can’t remember the last time I missed a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s quite impatient, feels silly sitting still with his eyes closed, and tends to obsess or over-analyze just about everything, it’s been quite the journey. But I continue to come back to it every day because meditation’s had some powerful positive effects on my life. It’s helped me learn to be fully-present and listen during conversations, sleep better, and overcome some surprising anxieties (including a rather paralyzing fear of hospitals); but I’ll save these for another blog post. As the title suggests, I want to focus this one on the most significant takeaway I’ve had from all this sitting-with-my-eyes-closed-and-focusing-on-my-breath. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We cannot really control the sea, but we can learn to surf the waves”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I wouldn’t be surprised if you’ve heard something like this before. Sayings that amount to “control is an illusion” are oft-repeated nuggets of profound wisdom, especially from the mouths of meditation teachers. And when you really stop to think about it, it makes a lot of sense. Despite our desperate attempts to, it seems like we can’t really control most of the outcomes we’d like to. We can’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; control whether we get that promotion or not, whether this latest relationship will work out, or whether our names will go down in the history books for something. Sure, we can &lt;em&gt;influence&lt;/em&gt; these things: we can work hard or communicate better or try to do noteworthy things, but ultimately the outcomes are dependent on so many other things that it seems like we can’t really &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; these things happen (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesecret.tv/stories/ask-believe-receive-33/&quot;&gt;no matter what “The Secret” might have you believe&lt;/a&gt;). This can be an important, profound lesson: it’s probably a bad idea to chase such things, and an even worse idea to base our-self worth on them (Mark Manson puts this more eloquently &lt;a href=&quot;https://markmanson.net/not-giving-a-fuck&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). We should probably practice more gratitude, smell the roses more, and generally learn to be happier with our lives and the gifts we’ve been given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think this somewhat trite lesson was the full extent of the “surf the waves” teaching. So I continued sitting with my eyes closed every night and trying to gain better control of my thoughts and feelings. I started to become more aware of myself, and try to catch myself better whenever I got mad or sad or overly jealous. I learnt to recognize and intercept anxious thought cycles that showed up whenever I stepped foot in a hospital. I continued my practice with zeal after gaining these abilities because I thought that eventually I’d be able to &lt;em&gt;fully&lt;/em&gt; control my feelings and thoughts, to be able to be happy or focused or reflective at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was with this excitement and zeal that I started trying to control my thoughts more; to truly master focus, calm and patience. I envisioned myself becoming like a wise old Kung-Fu master from the movies; someone who seemed to grasp deep profundities of life and was always in control of themselves. This process ended up looking a little like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My thoughts 2 hours after I’ve forgotten to eat lunch&lt;/strong&gt;: Today has been a &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; day, just THE WORST. I’ve been so unproductive and useless even though I’ve spend all this (insert expletive) time trying to get this done. Everyone else seems to be just fine and doing much better than me; at this rate, I’m going to go no where in life and everything will just come crashing -
Wait!… Man, this is such a useless thought cycle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hah! I’ve realized it - I’ve become aware! Yes, the meditation is paying off! Alright, now time to fix it, let’s take a deep breath…. Good, now, it’s obvious I’m hungry. We’ll fix that soon, but let’s first concentrate on this problem set and get it done. I control my thoughts - &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 seconds later&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My brain&lt;/strong&gt;: That person who just walked in looked a lot like Sam Altman. Gee, I wonder what Sam Altman’s up to now; in fact, I wonder where he went to college, and who his parents were?
Let’s take a quick refresher break and check that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20 minutes into break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My brain&lt;/strong&gt;: Wow - he was doing cool things with his life even when he was 19. Damn - I’m not even doing cool things now… I’m really not going anywhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me: Wait! Again - it happened AGAIN!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/meditation-pics/shifu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Shifu Picture&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Unfortunately, I didn't attain inner peace like Master Shifu here, and he's not pleased...&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many more repeats of the above, I began to realize that leashing my thoughts and feelings to my whim was not really practical. “The Sea” from the saying was not just external, but also &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt;: the illusion of control seemed to run deeper than I’d originally thought. I realized I’d probably &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be able to stop feeling hangry, or insecure or anxious. And at first, this bothered me: I didn’t like the prospect that I’d &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be able to control my mind and stop feeling these things. The more I meditated and became aware of my thoughts, the more I realized how chaotic and reactive my thoughts really are. Try as I might to control them and change my reactions to things, it seemed my &lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2019/08/fire-light.html&quot;&gt;monkey mind&lt;/a&gt; would always find a way to win. It started to feel like all this meditating was getting me nowhere (and potentially even making me &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; at controlling myself)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, after a couple meditation sessions and some research, I started to realize this is simply the nature of things. All of us come packaged in bodies that are constantly pumped full of different hormones, bacteria and who-knows-what other things that influence our moods. Our brains have an amazing capacity for reason, empathy and care; but also can make us delusional or unnaturally sad or selfish. In totality, the evidence suggests our thoughts and feelings are biologically engineered to be influenced by an overwhelmingly complex web of factors; just one of which is our conscious will. So it’s not too surprising that I can’t will myself to be all sunshine-and-rainbows when I haven’t eaten for a day, or concentrate on work when I haven’t slept for the last 28 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sharonsalzberg.com/&quot;&gt;Sharon Salzberg&lt;/a&gt; expresses this idea nicely: “Why are you blaming yourself for this thought which has come up in your mind? Did you say that at 2 o’clock I’d like to be filled with fear or hatred? &lt;em&gt;No&lt;/em&gt; - but when conditions come together for (a thought or feeling) to arise, it will arise”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought this meant I should give up on meditation. After all, if the truth is simply that all my thoughts and feelings depend on all these external conditions, that I’m floating in a sea and fully at it’s mercy, then what’s the point?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I later realized, the point is that we do have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; control. We can learn to surf. More specifically, we can - provided we’re aware enough - choose to act differently than our whims would dictate. And through action, we can &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; the conditions we’re in and thus (admittedly roundaboutly) change whatever it is we’re thinking or feeling. A little bit of thought seems to confirm this. A soldier may never be able to stop being afraid of dying in battle, but they can train themselves to carry on with their mission regardless. A doctor may never get over the panic attack that comes with seeing a massive injury, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/healthcare-network/views-from-the-nhs-frontline/2018/jan/16/doctor-prone-fainting-how-got-over-it&quot;&gt;can choose to finish a surgery regardless&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, though much more mundane,
 I’ll probably never train myself to be able to focus when I’m hangry, but I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; decide to stop obsessing over my work and go eat something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As has been repeated to me time and time again, the point of meditation is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to change thought patterns; but rather to become more aware of them so I can stop being so yanked around by them and take steps to change the conditions that caused them in the first place. And realizing this means accepting 2 things: (1) that the future will bring times of sadness, heartache, loneliness and other not-so-fun things that will just happen to me no matter how much I try to control / stop them, and this is both natural and okay; but also (2) that I can take responsibility for how I choose to respond to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months since I’ve realized all this, my life - and those of most people around the globe - have been tumultuous to say the least. The Coronavirus has turned both the internal and external seas of my life into maelstroms. But the recognition that this is only natural, and moreover that I can do something about this, that I can take responsibility for my actions and find interesting ways of surfing this unprecedented storm, has made all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing what I’ll learn as my meditation journey continues!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><summary type="html">Here’s a screenshot from my profile page on the 10% Happier guided meditation App:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Main Undergrad College Essay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/My-Main-Undergrad-College-Essay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Main Undergrad College Essay" /><published>2019-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/My-Main-Undergrad-College-Essay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/My-Main-Undergrad-College-Essay/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been asked this a bunch of times and here it finally is: the essay I wrote for the CommonApp. I think it’s really representative of the headspace I was in at the time (and admittedly still am in, to some degree). If you’re reading this and struggling with college essay, then let me say that I’ve been there too and I’ve got advice: just write the most honest reflection of yourself. That’s it. And that’s what I attempted to do below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, I was accepted into Brown with this essay, but rejected pretty much everywhere else; though I don’t think you should read too much into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Patience is a virtue”. This was the answer I got to most questions I asked as a child.
Be it “What research should I do to win a Nobel Prize?”, or even “How do I go about making a Batman grapple
gun?”, I was always told to be patient.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re not old enough to do that yet”, they would reply, “You need to wait to grow up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hated waiting, especially for unknown, indeterminate amounts of time. But since everyone I asked told me
the same thing, I figured it must be true. So, I would force myself to wait and put all my ambitious ideas on hold
while I attempted to learn this supposed “virtue” of patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One effective way I found of passing my time was through reading. My love for reading soon kindled another
desire: to write something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every other desire or idea I’d ever had, this seemed great and perfectly plausible.
My mind immediately began dreaming up characters, plot, page counts, chapter names and even possible
publishers. I enthusiastically approached my fifth grade English teacher with my plans, confident that she too
would see the brilliance of my ideas and guide me forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great that you want to write.”, she said, “but good writing takes time. You have much more to learn. Remember, patience is a virtue”. Once again, my ideas were met with the exact same response: “patience is a
virtue”. But I didn’t understand patience, and I didn’t understand why I had to wait. So this time, instead of
abandoning my idea and resigning to patience, I decided to try. I was convinced I could do it, though there was still
the overwhelming feeling that everyone else was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I began writing. Surprisingly, it wasn’t as easy as I’d thought. There were so many times when I hit a dead end
and almost gave up. But I kept going, just to see if I could finish it. One year and 35,000 words later, I had a
completed manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t content: I wanted to get it published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great that you’ve written something, but you should probably wait till you older before you publish”, my friends
said. They’d never heard of a published author as young as I was. I hadn’t either, and like them, I was fairly certain
that I had to be patient and write something else to get published. But still, since I had come this far, I wanted to
try. So I sent my manuscript to a few online publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, I got a reply from a publisher interested in publishing my book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, that first book was officially published; the very same book that people told me would never get
published because I was too young.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my book did not become the record-breaking, Pulitzer-winning, multi-million bestseller that I had
hoped (JK Rowling made things look way too easy). Still, the fact that it was published represented something
huge for me: I didn’t have to be patient. I learnt that there is no such thing as “too young”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though looking back, that first book seems rather silly and juvenile, I would do it again given the opportunity.
The realization that I could challenge the “virtue” of patience helped me so much. Later on, it helped me lead my
robotics team to win Nationals and represent India despite the fact that other people told us we were “too young”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenging patience has led me to a new mantra: “Impatience is a virtue”. While patience is always important,
it’s the stubborn desire to be impatient, work hard and not wait for others that drives great accomplishments. Yes,
impatience might not always succeed, but I’d rather try and fail than wait around to grow older or gain other
people’s approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, no one ever changed the world by waiting around.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><summary type="html">I’ve been asked this a bunch of times and here it finally is: the essay I wrote for the CommonApp. I think it’s really representative of the headspace I was in at the time (and admittedly still am in, to some degree). If you’re reading this and struggling with college essay, then let me say that I’ve been there too and I’ve got advice: just write the most honest reflection of yourself. That’s it. And that’s what I attempted to do below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Innovation At Its Finest</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Innovation-at-its-finest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Innovation At Its Finest" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Innovation-at-its-finest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Innovation-at-its-finest/">&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I was attempting to run last-minute experiments to finish up a paper just in time for a conference deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/innovation-pics/Robot_Experiment.png&quot; alt=&quot;Robot Button Pressing&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project essentially involved getting our beautiful white robot-arm shown above to press the buttons on the panel in front of it. Unfortunately for us, our approach required lots of data of the robot pressing different buttons (captured with the camera you see on that tripod there). Fortunately for us though, I had automated the data collection – so I simply started my button-pressing script, left for the night and came back to find all the data we needed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to my great surprise, our algorithm failed rather catastrophically when I fed in this data. After hours of debugging, I realized that most of the images I’d collected had been dark. Literally – the camera feed had been pitch black. Someone had turned off the lights!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while spent wondering which evil, soulless person would so cruelly mess with our experiment right before a deadline, I found the culprit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/innovation-pics/switch.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auto Switch&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out the room had an automatic, motion-activated light switch…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This left me with a unique problem: I needed to find a way to keep the lights on. Being an Engineering student, I began searching for materials to construct something to fool the motion-sensor. I needed a solution that would be simple and fast-to-build given it was already late and I very much did not want to deal with this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I came up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/innovation-pics/disco_ball.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auto Switch&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what it looks like: a disco ball with a folded piece of paper taped to it. I chose a disco ball because its speed of rotation was slow enough that the sensor would register some movement (as opposed to a fan, which was my first idea). The paper was to fool the sensor into picking up actual movement…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was extremely proud of myself at the time. Now, the robot would collect the data we needed and I could happily walk in the next morning, ready to run experiments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for us, it turned out that the paper-on-a-disco-ball wasn’t a stroke of genius. I walked in the next morning to find a dark room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral of the story: if you choose to become a robotics researcher, know that you’ll encounter the weirdest, most unexpected and annoying bugs right before deadlines…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="For-Laughs" /><summary type="html">A while ago, I was attempting to run last-minute experiments to finish up a paper just in time for a conference deadline.</summary></entry></feed>