<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-07T11:57:09-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nishanth J. Kumar</title><subtitle>My personal homepage and blog for non-fictional musings</subtitle><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">My Goldwater Application Sample</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/My-Goldwater-Application-Sample/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Goldwater Application Sample" /><published>2020-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/My-Goldwater-Application-Sample</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/My-Goldwater-Application-Sample/">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, I had the incredible privilege of being named a Goldwater Scholar. While winning the scholarship was rather validating and motivating, I thought the application process worthwhile in of itself because it forced me to think hard about my research direction and career goals for the future. During the application process, I found it incredibly helpful to read past sample applications. However, such samples are pretty few and far between, especially within the Computer Science or Mathematics categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, I thought I’d put my own application online in the hopes that future Goldwater applicants find it helpful. Below, you’ll find my responses to all the short essay questions + my research essay; which represent the bulk of the Goldwater application. If you’re reading this and considering applying to the Goldwater but currently on the fence, I’d highly recommend you try it (especially if you’re a sophomore because you can apply again next year!). If you’re in no way planning to apply for the scholarship but just reading this anyways, I hope it’s at least mildly interesting / entertaining…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In one or two sentences, describe your career goals and professional aspirations (see example below). This statement will be used in publications if you are selected as a scholar or honorable mention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obtain a PhD in Artificial Intelligence. Conduct research aiming to develop intelligence algorithms to enable practical and collaborative robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are your career goals and professional aspirations? Indicate which area(s) of mathematics, science or engineering you are considering pursuing in your research career and specify how your current academic program and your overall educational plans will assist you in achieving your career goals and professional aspirations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been dreaming of creating intelligent robots for many centuries now. Intelligent and collaborative robots could enable everything from creating an extraterrestrial habitat on Mars to making nuclear fusion reactors a viable source of clean and safe energy. The potential applications of these robots are so vast that it seems like their development could fundamentally change the world for the better, similar to how computers have changed our world by an unprecedented factor in only the last 50 years. The prospect of having widespread intelligent and collaborative machines at our disposal is thus exciting indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, my primary career goal is to accelerate the development of such intelligent and collaborative robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that creating such robots is not a simple task in the slightest. Such intelligent and collaborative robots have not even been created in a laboratory setting yet. Hence, it is clear to me that I need to spend time learning as much as I can about these fields and attempt to advance the state-of-the-art in research as much as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, I am pursuing an undergraduate degree in Computer Engineering. I believe that to create truly useful robots, we must make progress in creating increasingly intelligent algorithms in addition to cheaper, more accurate sensors and actuators. Thus, I see the challenges of robotics as fundamentally being challenges of computer science and engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to study computer engineering because it enables me to gain foundational knowledge in both fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of my curriculum, I am a member of a Robotics and Artificial Intelligence lab on campus. As a lab member, I am able to learn and work on independent research projects to advance the current state-of-the-art in various sub-fields like Planning, Reinforcement Learning, Imitation Learning and Human-Robot Interaction. I am also able to constantly learn about the field from my fellow researchers within the lab and around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduation, I intend to pursue a Ph.D. in Computer Science with a focus on artificial intelligence for robots. I want to build upon the foundation I will have laid to focus both on developing intelligence algorithms for robots and on creating interfaces to facilitate better human-robot collaboration. At the completion of my Ph.D., I hope to have made significant contributions to the state-of-the-art for robot learning and be well-equipped to help build the robots of our dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Describe an activity or experience that has been important in helping shape or reinforce your desire to pursue a research career in science, mathematics or engineering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first research internship involved helping a colleague with his project: using data from expert demonstrations to teach a robot how to press buttons. My colleague already had an algorithm; all that was left was to implement it on our lab’s mobile robot. We didn’t think this would take more than two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, we were very wrong. Our initial attempts resulted in our robot’s arm frequently hitting obstacles. Some weeks of debugging yielded a flaw in our algorithm. Some more weeks and extensive tests revealed our data-collection programs weren’t actually collecting data. Weeks continued to pass until my colleague graduated and we lost hope that the idea would work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, on the urging of an advisor, another colleague and I began re-examining the project. We ran meticulous experiments until we finally discovered a small error with our data collection. Days later, approximately one year after having gotten involved in the project, I held my breath and watched the robot press a button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While button-pressing may seem a trivial task, that moment was one of the most profound experiences of my life. Despite the many setbacks and frustrations, I continue with research to this day because such moments of discovery, of knowing that I have created something significant, novel and potentially impactful, have made everything else well worth it. Research is the most exciting and fulfilling pursuit I have ever known and I’m excited to spend the rest of my life doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Goldwater Scholars will be representative of the diverse economic, ethnic and occupational backgrounds of families in the United States. Describe any social and/or economic impacts you have encountered that influenced your education - either positively or negatively - and how you have dealt with them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in my father’s relatively small hometown in South India where opportunities were scarce. My high school had no guidance counselor and the nearest SAT Testing Center was a three-hour drive. However, my parents are both hard-working immigrants to the US who taught me to dream big and then persevere relentlessly for those dreams. So, I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I taught myself electronics and computer programming and began competing in national - and eventually international - robotics competitions and science fairs. I took a ninety-minute bus ride every day for six years to attend my city’s only international school. Eventually, I was able to achieve my dream of being accepted to study engineering at a research-driven college in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should emphasize that I’ve had the good fortune of being supported by great people throughout my journey thus far. My parents have never spared expenses on my education or pursuit of opportunity. My high school teachers nominated me for every relevant extracurricular opportunity they could and stayed after school hours to mentor me. My school’s chairman even fully-sponsored our Robotics team when costs became prohibitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experiences have taught me that it’s important to encourage and support students everywhere to pursue opportunity, no matter how scarce it may be. Sometimes, this support can change a life, as it did mine. In this spirit, I hope that my career and life can contribute to making the world have more opportunity for everyone, everywhere.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/images/goldwater-sample-pics/Nishanth_s_Goldwater_Research_Essay.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;p style=&quot;font-size:20px&quot;&gt; My Research Essay &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(PS: If you’re looking to write your Research Essay in LaTex, I’d highly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overleaf.com/latex/templates/goldwater-scholarship-research-essay-template/pmhbjqwgvdvb&quot;&gt;this free, open-source template&lt;/a&gt; by 2019 Goldwater Scholar Thomas Richards).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Earlier this year, I had the incredible privilege of being named a Goldwater Scholar. While winning the scholarship was rather validating and motivating, I thought the application process worthwhile in of itself because it forced me to think hard about my research direction and career goals for the future. During the application process, I found it incredibly helpful to read past sample applications. However, such samples are pretty few and far between, especially within the Computer Science or Mathematics categories.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I Learned From 500 Days Of Meditation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/What-I-Learned-From-500-Days-Of-Meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I Learned From 500 Days Of Meditation" /><published>2020-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/What-I-Learned-From-500-Days-Of-Meditation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/What-I-Learned-From-500-Days-Of-Meditation/">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a screenshot from my profile page on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tenpercent.com/&quot;&gt;10% Happier&lt;/a&gt; guided meditation App:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/meditation-pics/screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;App Screenshot&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;It's been a lot of sitting-with-my-eyes-closed&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As of today, I’ve meditated for just over 500 days total with this app. My meditation habit actually started before getting the app, and I didn’t log a few days here and there, so overall I’ve probably been meditating somewhere around 600 days; averaging between 5 and 10 minutes each day. I can’t remember the last time I missed a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s quite impatient, feels silly sitting still with his eyes closed, and tends to obsess or over-analyze just about everything, it’s been quite the journey. But I continue to come back to it every day because meditation’s had some powerful positive effects on my life. It’s helped me learn to be fully-present and listen during conversations, sleep better, and overcome some surprising anxieties (including a rather paralyzing fear of hospitals); but I’ll save these for another blog post. As the title suggests, I want to focus this one on the most significant takeaway I’ve had from all this sitting-with-my-eyes-closed-and-focusing-on-my-breath. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We cannot really control the sea, but we can learn to surf the waves”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I wouldn’t be surprised if you’ve heard something like this before. Sayings that amount to “control is an illusion” are oft-repeated nuggets of profound wisdom, especially from the mouths of meditation teachers. And when you really stop to think about it, it makes a lot of sense. Despite our desperate attempts to, it seems like we can’t really control most of the outcomes we’d like to. We can’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; control whether we get that promotion or not, whether this latest relationship will work out, or whether our names will go down in the history books for something. Sure, we can &lt;em&gt;influence&lt;/em&gt; these things: we can work hard or communicate better or try to do noteworthy things, but ultimately the outcomes are dependent on so many other things that it seems like we can’t really &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; these things happen (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesecret.tv/stories/ask-believe-receive-33/&quot;&gt;no matter what “The Secret” might have you believe&lt;/a&gt;). This can be an important, profound lesson: it’s probably a bad idea to chase such things, and an even worse idea to base our-self worth on them (Mark Manson puts this more eloquently &lt;a href=&quot;https://markmanson.net/not-giving-a-fuck&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). We should probably practice more gratitude, smell the roses more, and generally learn to be happier with our lives and the gifts we’ve been given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think this somewhat trite lesson was the full extent of the “surf the waves” teaching. So I continued sitting with my eyes closed every night and trying to gain better control of my thoughts and feelings. I started to become more aware of myself, and try to catch myself better whenever I got mad or sad or overly jealous. I learnt to recognize and intercept anxious thought cycles that showed up whenever I stepped foot in a hospital. I continued my practice with zeal after gaining these abilities because I thought that eventually I’d be able to &lt;em&gt;fully&lt;/em&gt; control my feelings and thoughts, to be able to be happy or focused or reflective at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was with this excitement and zeal that I started trying to control my thoughts more; to truly master focus, calm and patience. I envisioned myself becoming like a wise old Kung-Fu master from the movies; someone who seemed to grasp deep profundities of life and was always in control of themselves. This process ended up looking a little like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My thoughts 2 hours after I’ve forgotten to eat lunch&lt;/strong&gt;: Today has been a &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; day, just THE WORST. I’ve been so unproductive and useless even though I’ve spend all this (insert expletive) time trying to get this done. Everyone else seems to be just fine and doing much better than me; at this rate, I’m going to go no where in life and everything will just come crashing -
Wait!… Man, this is such a useless thought cycle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hah! I’ve realized it - I’ve become aware! Yes, the meditation is paying off! Alright, now time to fix it, let’s take a deep breath…. Good, now, it’s obvious I’m hungry. We’ll fix that soon, but let’s first concentrate on this problem set and get it done. I control my thoughts - &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 seconds later&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My brain&lt;/strong&gt;: That person who just walked in looked a lot like Sam Altman. Gee, I wonder what Sam Altman’s up to now; in fact, I wonder where he went to college, and who his parents were?
Let’s take a quick refresher break and check that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20 minutes into break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My brain&lt;/strong&gt;: Wow - he was doing cool things with his life even when he was 19. Damn - I’m not even doing cool things now… I’m really not going anywhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me: Wait! Again - it happened AGAIN!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/meditation-pics/shifu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Shifu Picture&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Unfortunately, I didn't attain inner peace like Master Shifu here, and he's not pleased...&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many more repeats of the above, I began to realize that leashing my thoughts and feelings to my whim was not really practical. “The Sea” from the saying was not just external, but also &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt;: the illusion of control seemed to run deeper than I’d originally thought. I realized I’d probably &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be able to stop feeling hangry, or insecure or anxious. And at first, this bothered me: I didn’t like the prospect that I’d &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be able to control my mind and stop feeling these things. The more I meditated and became aware of my thoughts, the more I realized how chaotic and reactive my thoughts really are. Try as I might to control them and change my reactions to things, it seemed my &lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2019/08/fire-light.html&quot;&gt;monkey mind&lt;/a&gt; would always find a way to win. It started to feel like all this meditating was getting me nowhere (and potentially even making me &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; at controlling myself)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, after a couple meditation sessions and some research, I started to realize this is simply the nature of things. All of us come packaged in bodies that are constantly pumped full of different hormones, bacteria and who-knows-what other things that influence our moods. Our brains have an amazing capacity for reason, empathy and care; but also can make us delusional or unnaturally sad or selfish. In totality, the evidence suggests our thoughts and feelings are biologically engineered to be influenced by an overwhelmingly complex web of factors; just one of which is our conscious will. So it’s not too surprising that I can’t will myself to be all sunshine-and-rainbows when I haven’t eaten for a day, or concentrate on work when I haven’t slept for the last 28 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sharonsalzberg.com/&quot;&gt;Sharon Salzberg&lt;/a&gt; expresses this idea nicely: “Why are you blaming yourself for this thought which has come up in your mind? Did you say that at 2 o’clock I’d like to be filled with fear or hatred? &lt;em&gt;No&lt;/em&gt; - but when conditions come together for (a thought or feeling) to arise, it will arise”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought this meant I should give up on meditation. After all, if the truth is simply that all my thoughts and feelings depend on all these external conditions, that I’m floating in a sea and fully at it’s mercy, then what’s the point?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I later realized, the point is that we do have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; control. We can learn to surf. More specifically, we can - provided we’re aware enough - choose to act differently than our whims would dictate. And through action, we can &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; the conditions we’re in and thus (admittedly roundaboutly) change whatever it is we’re thinking or feeling. A little bit of thought seems to confirm this. A soldier may never be able to stop being afraid of dying in battle, but they can train themselves to carry on with their mission regardless. A doctor may never get over the panic attack that comes with seeing a massive injury, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/healthcare-network/views-from-the-nhs-frontline/2018/jan/16/doctor-prone-fainting-how-got-over-it&quot;&gt;can choose to finish a surgery regardless&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, though much more mundane,
 I’ll probably never train myself to be able to focus when I’m hangry, but I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; decide to stop obsessing over my work and go eat something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As has been repeated to me time and time again, the point of meditation is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to change thought patterns; but rather to become more aware of them so I can stop being so yanked around by them and take steps to change the conditions that caused them in the first place. And realizing this means accepting 2 things: (1) that the future will bring times of sadness, heartache, loneliness and other not-so-fun things that will just happen to me no matter how much I try to control / stop them, and this is both natural and okay; but also (2) that I can take responsibility for how I choose to respond to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months since I’ve realized all this, my life - and those of most people around the globe - have been tumultuous to say the least. The Coronavirus has turned both the internal and external seas of my life into maelstroms. But the recognition that this is only natural, and moreover that I can do something about this, that I can take responsibility for my actions and find interesting ways of surfing this unprecedented storm, has made all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing what I’ll learn as my meditation journey continues!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><summary type="html">Here’s a screenshot from my profile page on the 10% Happier guided meditation App:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Main College Essay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/My-Main-College-Essay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Main College Essay" /><published>2019-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/My-Main-College-Essay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/My-Main-College-Essay/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been asked this a bunch of times and here it finally is: the essay I wrote for the CommonApp. I think it’s really representative of the headspace I was in at the time (and admittedly still am in, to some degree). If you’re reading this and struggling with college essay, then let me say that I’ve been there too and I’ve got advice: just write the most honest reflection of yourself. That’s it. And that’s what I attempted to do below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, I was accepted into Brown with this essay, but rejected pretty much everywhere else; though I don’t think you should read too much into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Patience is a virtue”. This was the answer I got to most questions I asked as a child.
Be it “What research should I do to win a Nobel Prize?”, or even “How do I go about making a Batman grapple
gun?”, I was always told to be patient.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re not old enough to do that yet”, they would reply, “You need to wait to grow up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hated waiting, especially for unknown, indeterminate amounts of time. But since everyone I asked told me
the same thing, I figured it must be true. So, I would force myself to wait and put all my ambitious ideas on hold
while I attempted to learn this supposed “virtue” of patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One effective way I found of passing my time was through reading. My love for reading soon kindled another
desire: to write something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every other desire or idea I’d ever had, this seemed great and perfectly plausible.
My mind immediately began dreaming up characters, plot, page counts, chapter names and even possible
publishers. I enthusiastically approached my fifth grade English teacher with my plans, confident that she too
would see the brilliance of my ideas and guide me forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great that you want to write.”, she said, “but good writing takes time. You have much more to learn. Remember, patience is a virtue”. Once again, my ideas were met with the exact same response: “patience is a
virtue”. But I didn’t understand patience, and I didn’t understand why I had to wait. So this time, instead of
abandoning my idea and resigning to patience, I decided to try. I was convinced I could do it, though there was still
the overwhelming feeling that everyone else was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I began writing. Surprisingly, it wasn’t as easy as I’d thought. There were so many times when I hit a dead end
and almost gave up. But I kept going, just to see if I could finish it. One year and 35,000 words later, I had a
completed manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t content: I wanted to get it published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great that you’ve written something, but you should probably wait till you older before you publish”, my friends
said. They’d never heard of a published author as young as I was. I hadn’t either, and like them, I was fairly certain
that I had to be patient and write something else to get published. But still, since I had come this far, I wanted to
try. So I sent my manuscript to a few online publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, I got a reply from a publisher interested in publishing my book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, that first book was officially published; the very same book that people told me would never get
published because I was too young.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my book did not become the record-breaking, Pulitzer-winning, multi-million bestseller that I had
hoped (JK Rowling made things look way too easy). Still, the fact that it was published represented something
huge for me: I didn’t have to be patient. I learnt that there is no such thing as “too young”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though looking back, that first book seems rather silly and juvenile, I would do it again given the opportunity.
The realization that I could challenge the “virtue” of patience helped me so much. Later on, it helped me lead my
robotics team to win Nationals and represent India despite the fact that other people told us we were “too young”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenging patience has led me to a new mantra: “Impatience is a virtue”. While patience is always important,
it’s the stubborn desire to be impatient, work hard and not wait for others that drives great accomplishments. Yes,
impatience might not always succeed, but I’d rather try and fail than wait around to grow older or gain other
people’s approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, no one ever changed the world by waiting around.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><summary type="html">I’ve been asked this a bunch of times and here it finally is: the essay I wrote for the CommonApp. I think it’s really representative of the headspace I was in at the time (and admittedly still am in, to some degree). If you’re reading this and struggling with college essay, then let me say that I’ve been there too and I’ve got advice: just write the most honest reflection of yourself. That’s it. And that’s what I attempted to do below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Innovation At Its Finest</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Innovation-at-its-finest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Innovation At Its Finest" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Innovation-at-its-finest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Innovation-at-its-finest/">&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I was attempting to run last-minute experiments to finish up a paper just in time for a conference deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/innovation-pics/Robot_Experiment.png&quot; alt=&quot;Robot Button Pressing&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project essentially involved getting our beautiful white robot-arm shown above to press the buttons on the panel in front of it. Unfortunately for us, our approach required lots of data of the robot pressing different buttons (captured with the camera you see on that tripod there). Fortunately for us though, I had automated the data collection – so I simply started my button-pressing script, left for the night and came back to find all the data we needed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to my great surprise, our algorithm failed rather catastrophically when I fed in this data. After hours of debugging, I realized that most of the images I’d collected had been dark. Literally – the camera feed had been pitch black. Someone had turned off the lights!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while spent wondering which evil, soulless person would so cruelly mess with our experiment right before a deadline, I found the culprit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/innovation-pics/switch.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auto Switch&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out the room had an automatic, motion-activated light switch…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This left me with a unique problem: I needed to find a way to keep the lights on. Being an Engineering student, I began searching for materials to construct something to fool the motion-sensor. I needed a solution that would be simple and fast-to-build given it was already late and I very much did not want to deal with this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I came up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/innovation-pics/disco_ball.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auto Switch&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what it looks like: a disco ball with a folded piece of paper taped to it. I chose a disco ball because its speed of rotation was slow enough that the sensor would register some movement (as opposed to a fan, which was my first idea). The paper was to fool the sensor into picking up actual movement…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was extremely proud of myself at the time. Now, the robot would collect the data we needed and I could happily walk in the next morning, ready to run experiments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for us, it turned out that the paper-on-a-disco-ball wasn’t a stroke of genius. I walked in the next morning to find a dark room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral of the story: if you choose to become a robotics researcher, know that you’ll encounter the weirdest, most unexpected and annoying bugs right before deadlines…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="For-Laughs" /><summary type="html">A while ago, I was attempting to run last-minute experiments to finish up a paper just in time for a conference deadline.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts And Robots From Icra 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Some-thoughts-and-robots-from-ICRA-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts And Robots From Icra 2019" /><published>2019-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Some-thoughts-and-robots-from-ICRA-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Some-thoughts-and-robots-from-ICRA-2019/">&lt;p&gt;Some weeks ago, I had the pleasure of attending the 36th International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) in Montreal, Canada. This was my first major Robotics and AI focused conference and it was probably one of the most interesting and learning-intensive weeks I’ve ever had. This post is an overview of my conference experience, most-interesting things I learnt, most-exciting research directions I saw and cool robots that were on display!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you’d prefer a tl;dr summary and my big takeaways from the conference, scroll all the way down)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;interesting-ideas-and-learnings&quot;&gt;Interesting ideas and learnings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-causal-inference-for-deep-learning&quot;&gt;1. Causal Inference for Deep Learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoshua Bengio opened the conference with a talk that was about his current thoughts on Machine Learning – specifically Deep Learning – as a field and some corresponding research his group (MILA) has been working on. The big idea he presented was this: all current ML methods – Deep Learning included – cannot generalize from a distribution. Bengio believes the way to do this is to disentangle input data to discover causal relationships that will hold for other data. He believes this causal inference is a key feature of human intelligence and hat incorporating it could not only make Deep Learning generalize better, but also be more explainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He believes incorporating general priors/assumptions into ML models will help us learn with more sample-efficiency and discover causality. In particular, he wants to use the ‘independent mechanism’ idea which is inspired from Physics and the general independence of objects in the world and laid out in this paper. Some early experiments he’s conducted have shown that correct causal models leads to much faster adaptation to new tasks (I.e, better Transfer Learning) and much greater sample-efficiency – which is as one would expect. He also talked about achieving meta-learning with causal-inference agents: he envisions an outer loop that uses evolution to optimize an inner-loops causal-learning objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that Bengio is one of the people that invented modern Deep Learning (and recently won the Turing Award for it too!), I was hoping for more big-ideas and high-level thoughts and insights from his talk. However, he ended up getting pretty technical and moving fairly quickly, which made it difficult to really appreciate all the concepts he showed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely agree with Bengio’s motivation to incorporate more causal-inference into Deep Learning and ML in general. While I think there are many other things one might work on within Deep Learning, causal inference could very well be the ‘next big thing’ that pushes the field forward. I personally have not yet read too much about the theory of causal inference, but I have read some of Judea Pearl’s work and am convinced the lack of a causal model is a significant theoretical limitation of how intelligent our AI agents can actually become. Seeing that Bengio (and evidently many others) appear to be heeding Pearl’s latest call for more ML researchers to work on causal models makes me want to take a deep-dive into the theory of causality and into the current efforts to algorithmitize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-drones&quot;&gt;2. Drones&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robotics is a staggeringly huge field and consequently, there’s so many interesting sub-fields I just haven’t had the bandwidth to look into. Drones are one of these. Still, before this conference, I’d never really thought that drones had real-world applications the military or taking Facebook-worthy selfies. Boy was I wrong…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijay Kumar of UPenn’s GRASP Lab delivered perhaps my favorite plenary of the conference. He started off giving a brief representative diagram of where he thinks drone research is at the moment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/VijayKumar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vijay Kumar&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, no one thought drones would have significant commercial application until around 2010, when a low buzz of VC and consumer interest began. This grew until an explosion in 2015, when DJI (who happened to be at ICRA) sold tens of millions of drones worldwide buoyed by significant interest in drone selfies and photography/video in general. Interest in drones followed the Garner Hype Cycle [link!] till it petered out in 2018. Apparently, all the investors and entrepreneurs interested in the space didn’t give up; they simply moved to flying cars instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumar himself has a rather interesting opinion on drones both from a commercial and research perspective. As an entrepreneur, he believes there’s still significant business opportunity for drones: just not for personal or military applications. He’s excited by the opportunity to use drones to make solutions for large businesses, which apparently almost no one else is doing at the moment. In fact, he runs a startup that uses drones to create detailed maps of mines for mining companies: something that is incredibly painstaking and dangerous today (evidently, the company is very successful so far). As a researcher and professor, he believes the incremental improvements in drones (things like flight-stabilization and very reliable people/face-tracking, etc.) should be left to industry. He’s interested in what drones will need to be really good at for applications 10 years out from hitting the markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijay spent a significant portion of his talk explaining why drones are so hard. Essentially, there’s all the problems you would have with a mobile robot (partially-observable environments, noisy sensor data, etc.) plus the fact that the drone needs to remain in flight: a high-dimensional and difficult problem in of itself. However, at the end of the talk, he explained why drones still excite him despite all these issues. Aside from things like automated, quick deliveries, he’s extremely excited about the potential for swarms of drones to coordinate and create large-scale, highly-detailed semantic maps. This may not seem like a world-changing application at first, but Vijay pointed out efforts to apply such technology to search-and-rescue, exploration of difficult environments and even disaster recovery at Fukushima. He thinks that this is just one of the many use-cases for large-scale drone deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I still think mobile, ground based robots are cooler than drones, Vijay Kumar’s talk and work makes me think I could see myself working with drones if given the right opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-robotics-as-the-maturation-of-machine-learning&quot;&gt;3. Robotics as the maturation of Machine Learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most unique (and totally unexpected) experience I had at ICRA was when I got the opportunity to meet a personal idol: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Goodfellow&quot;&gt;Ian Goodfellow&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t heard of him, Ian invented GAN’s (Generative Adversarial Networks), was a high-profile researcher at Google and OpenAI and is , generally considered one of the foremost Machine Learning experts on the planet. He recently left his job at Google to join Apple, which is why he was at the conference (Apple had a booth there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian talked a bit about his views on current GAN and neural network research in general, along with other technical topics, but what I found most interesting was when we began talking about robotics. Ian wasn’t allowed to say much about the project(s) he joined Apple to work on, but it evidently has a lot to do with robotics; and I really wanted to know why. Why would he leave a high-ranking role at Google where he was doing what he worked on during his PhD?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian obviously had numerous reasons. Firstly, he views robotics as the next big frontier for machine learning. Thus far, most of ML and AI has progressed in the virtual world: run and evaluated in simulated worlds with often highly-controlled environments. But robots operate in the real world, where things aren’t perfectly deterministic, information is heavily noisy and every problem is incredibly high-dimensional. Goodfellow thinks that scaling ML up to tackle these problems is akin to the field “growing up” from infancy. Secondly, Ian is convinced that creating robust, real-world autonomous systems is the most significant engineering project humanity has ever undertaken. He referenced an article by Vinod Khosla [Link!] where Khosla attempted to answer the question “How much money would it take to create really good healthcare in India?”. The article essentially concludes it would take more than 100 billion dollars. Khosla consequently concludes that we can’t solve current major problems like healthcare with just policy solutions. Goodfellow believes that real-world autonomous systems like robots could be the technology that enables not only this, but helps us deal with climate change and aging populations. Finally, Ian said that he’s always really like robots. Apparently, just after he graduated from Stanford, he got an internship at Willow Garage. He loved the company and mission so much that his “Plan A” in life was to simply work for Willow. However, they wouldn’t hire him without a PhD, so he went to go do that with the full intent to come back and get the job he was promised. However, Willow Garage unfortunately went bankrupt and (fortunately), Ian’s deep learning research really took off. So, he stayed a deep learning researcher for a while until he got the opportunity from Apple to come back to doing what he originally intended to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hearing this from Goodfellow was both surprising and incredibly reassuring. I’ve believed in robotics’ potential for a while now, but I do often wonder if I’m wrong, or if it will take longer than my lifetime for us to begin to see intelligent robots. The fact that Goodfellow and others like him believe in robotics as well seems to be a good sign that the field’s potential is bright and also soon-to-come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-if-running-a-startup-is-a-marathon-running-a-robotics-startup-is-a-decathlon&quot;&gt;4. If running a startup is a marathon, running a robotics startup is a decathlon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of the conference, the Greg Dudek (the General Chair), stated that this year’s ICRA was the largest robotics conference in history (2163 total paper submissions). A good portion of these attendees were people interested in business/industry applications of robotics and AI. Apparently, the organizing committee had sold out the original space planned for company booths, re-planned and doubled the space, and then sold that out too. So there were a lot of companies and thus a general interest in commercialization of the technologies being displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Gariepy is the CTO of &lt;a href=&quot;https://clearpathrobotics.com/about-clearpath-story/&quot;&gt;Clearpath Robotics&lt;/a&gt; and has been a serial robotics entrepreneur for decades now. I got to attend his keynote talk where he talked about what starting a robotics company is like and how to be successful at one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some points I thought were particularly insightful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robotics startups are hard because robots are often complicated and need hardware and software to work together seamlessly. This requires engineers that know both hardware and software&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lots of robotics companies pitch themselves as a ‘platform’. They point to successes like Apple’s App Store or YouTube. However, a key thing they forget is that platform companies need to start with users. Apple sold millions of iPhones before the App Store launched. Launching a platform for developers/customers without first having users is generally not a good idea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Companies should be very clear about how they plan to make money. They should validate the fact that people will pay for their robots/services before building them. One way to build a valid business is to be not just a robotics company. For example, Walmart is a profitable store chain, but they also have an invincible supply chain. Companies should explore models beyond simply building and selling robots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common failure modes for robotics companies:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is no real value proposition&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The company is perpetually in pilot mode / research and the money eventually runs out&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many people starting robotics companies come from academia / research. It’s easy to fall into the trap of thinking that running a company is like running a research lab, but this is not true.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remember that you are running a company, not just building cool robots. The customer matters more than the robot’s technical complexity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Know exactly where robotics fits into your businesses&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t just declare a competitive advantage, validate it!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite constantly reiterating that robotics companies are difficult, Ryan ended with some reasons why he thinks they present unparalleled opportunity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Climate change will have massive economic side effects in the need for quick and significant infrastructure changes. It’s going to be incredibly difficult if not impossible to meet these requirements with manual labor. We need robots!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The space of the three D’s (Dull, Dirty and Dangerous) tasks that robots could take over could disrupt trillion dollar industries like mining, transportation and construction. Demand for these services (and others in Maslow’s hierarchy of needs) isn’t going anywhere, so this could be extremely profitable in the long term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who wanted to build a direct to consumer ‘platform’ robotics company, this talk was both educational and demoralizing. I stayed after the talk to chat with Ryan and am fairly convinced that he’s extremely knowledgeable about the robotics space and gave sound advice (so maybe I’ll start a robotics company that focuses on one of the 3 D’s instead). It was also incredibly exciting to hear about both the economic and world-changing potential of robotics (so perhaps I’m in the right field after all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-dealing-with-failure-as-a-robotics-researcher&quot;&gt;5. Dealing with failure as a robotics researcher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t something technical at all, but I wanted to include it because I found it really significant. Matthew Mason – a long time roboticist and Professor at CMU’s legendary Robotics Institute – delivered a funny and interesting keynote that was all about failure. My takeaways from it were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ideas are cheap – success in research is all about the work you put into it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you talk a lot about your own failures, people will generally think that you’re cool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When to give up on an idea: never! But that doesn’t mean keep bashing your head against the wall: simply move the idea lower in your priority queue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t trust ideas from smart people (especially yourself). If you hear a good idea from a smart person, it may be that you think it’s good because of the person’s reputation. But if you hear a good idea from a person you think is generally stupid, then you can be fairly certain this is genuinely a good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Failure drives research and also the field. What doesn’t work is valuable knowledge because it guides the search for what does. So fail often and don’t be sad!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;robots&quot;&gt;Robots!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a lot of cool robots at ICRA this year (as one might expect). Unfortunately, I didn’t have the good sense to take pictures of all the things I saw. However, I did manage to get a few…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/clearpath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clearpath&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/hi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robot saying hi&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/sly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robot being sly&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/davinci.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The da Vinci Robot&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/art.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robot Art!&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ICRA-pics/spot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Boston Dynamics Spot!&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-general-takeaways-from-the-conference&quot;&gt;My general takeaways from the conference&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This field is happening now! Lots of opportunity&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This year’s ICRA was the biggest every robotics conference, with over 100 different companies attending and (most) attempting to recruit people. There seems to be so much opportunity and (perhaps more importantly) plenty of people willing to invest heavily in the field, both in terms of time and money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI + ML integrating more and more into robotics&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The top category of papers submitted was in Deep Learning for Robotics and Automation (and if you’re interested, here’s a really well-made tableau board allowing you to visualize all data about the people and papers from the conference). ‘Learning and Adaptive Systems’ and ‘Learning from Demonstration’ were also in the top 10 popular topics. It used to be that robotics conferences were dominated by work in controls, mechanics, etc. But more and more, they’re becoming dominated by AI and ML methods. I think this is a good idea for all fields involved; perhaps robotics truly is the ‘growing up’ of ML.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Self driving cars are the elephant in the room&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;From Waymo  to Uber, almost every single self-driving company I know of was at ICRA. And all of them are pushing hard to be first-to-market. Many people seem to share the opinion that self-driving cars could be the first massively-successful and widespread consumer-facing robotics project to succeed. While this is exciting indeed, I’d be careful not to count my chickens before they hatch. Many technologies (and even many robots) have gone through a phase of hype and seemed like the ‘next big thing’. It remains to be seen whether self-driving cars will actually live up to the hype.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the conference made me extremely excited to be a researcher in the field (which is perhaps by design). While it was great to see exciting new research and such interest from industry, there was also what seemed like a clear divide between the two (both at the conference venue and in general). Despite all the interesting papers, a lot of the research work was quite specific and seemed difficult to reproduce either because there was no shared code or because the setup would be too difficult to recreate. It doesn’t seem like most of the work will be integrated into work being done in industry anytime soon. While this isn’t the immediate explicit intent of research, I think we would benefit from creating more robust and reproducible systems that industry could use in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As insightful and eye-opening as this conference was for me, it also left me with some questions I hope to make some progress on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What support systems and architecture (along the line of things like ROS) would we need to enable more robust and reproducible research? How could we build platforms that the entire community would agree upon, adopt and build their own projects on?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do we need to work on to push the boundaries of robotics? How can we make widespread, intelligent and collaborative robots a reality?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to see all the new things robots will do in the coming years!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Conference" /><summary type="html">Some weeks ago, I had the pleasure of attending the 36th International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) in Montreal, Canada. This was my first major Robotics and AI focused conference and it was probably one of the most interesting and learning-intensive weeks I’ve ever had. This post is an overview of my conference experience, most-interesting things I learnt, most-exciting research directions I saw and cool robots that were on display!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Robots? Deciding What I Want To Do With My Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/why-robots-deciding-what-I-want-to-do-with-my-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Robots? Deciding What I Want To Do With My Life" /><published>2019-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/why-robots?-deciding-what-I-want-to-do-with-my-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/why-robots-deciding-what-I-want-to-do-with-my-life/">&lt;p&gt;Ever since my parents bought me my first robotic toy as a kid, I’ve been excited about robots. Over the years, I’ve been lucky enough to have had numerous opportunities to work with robots. I’ve played with toys, spent multiple years building Lego and heavy-metal robots for competitions, and most-recently done research with robots. So, when it came time for me to seriously consider what I want to do with the rest of my life, ‘work with robots’ was the first and natural choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while ago, a friend asked me a simple question: ‘why robots?’. I was quite surprised that this was a question at all: there are so many obvious answers. The more relevant question should’ve been ‘why not robots?’. When my friend pointed out that that wasn’t a sufficient answer, I realized I hadn’t really thought through all my reasons for wanting to work with robots. I’m a big believer in carefully and consciously reasoning from first principles when it comes to major life decisions, so it was quite alarming that I didn’t have a satisfactory answer to the simple question of ‘why robots?’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a long while thinking about my answer to this fundamental question and fortunately came up with one that I find quite satisfactory. This essay is an attempt to capture and record that answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why robots you ask?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-greatest-tool-ever-invented&quot;&gt;The Greatest Tool Ever Invented&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple millennia ago, Homo Sapiens’ lives were quite difficult indeed. The primary concern was food: most Sapiens got hungry at least once every day, and the only solution was to find and consume food. Unfortunately, food didn’t just show up at a centralized location, it usually needed to be hunted. Sapiens needed to chase and kill animals that – to our ancestors’ great annoyance – didn’t want to be killed and eaten. To make existence more annoying, some animals wanted to chase and kill the Sapiens. This presented a difficult existential dilemma: the Sapiens needed to get food without becoming food themselves. This was quite a problem indeed because many of the animals were bigger, stronger and deadlier than the Sapiens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Sapiens made an important discovery. They realized that these ubiquitous things we call rocks were quite hard. This was a useful property, because the rocks could be used to inflict injuries. However, it was difficult to completely kill an animal with the rocks. At some point, a couple Sapiens realized they could sharpen rocks. They fashioned the first crude axes and spears. Suddenly, hunting and protecting themselves became much easier. Suddenly, they moved to the top of the food chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ancestors’ discovery and use of rocks might seem trivial or irrelevant, but it is arguably one of the most significant events in human history. Those rocks were our first tools. The discovery and use of tools is considered a unique sign of intelligence. In fact, it is this ability to create tools that’s enabled modern life. From crude spears and axes, we moved on to fire, then clothing, then bricks for construction, then metalworking, then the wheel, then eventually the printing press and later the steam engine, then the electric motor and generator, then the telephone and the electric light bulb, then the transistor which paved the way for the computer and more recently, the Internet. The entire field of technology, the reason that our species expanded from a few scattered tribes to occupy every continent with 8 billion total individuals, is essentially an exercise in understanding the laws of the natural world and using these laws to build tools that will help us exploit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/why-robots-pics/flying_cars.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flying Cars&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And intelligent robots might just be the greatest tool we’ve ever invented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like previous world-changing tools, robots have an unprecedented potential to enable. Human bodies have significant limitations: we cannot survive radiation or extreme temperatures and are quite easily injured. With robots, we could spend years constructing extraterrestrial habitats before the first humans would arrive to settle them, we could operate nuclear power stations with an unprecedented level of safety, and we could enable the physically-disabled to do almost any task a normal person could do. Humans are prone to making avoidable mistakes. Robots are much less prone to failure in previously-seen environments, and they could enable us to save lives in medical diagnosis and routine surgery. Humans can’t thrive with a prolonged lack of food, water or sleep and do not enjoy performing repetitive drudgery. Robots could perform drudgery round-the-clock with minimal power and thus enable us to produce and distribute enough resources for every human on Earth to survive and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent robots have a seemingly endless number of applications. However, the most transformative applications might be those that are impossible to fathom today. When pioneers like Charles Babbage, Alan Turing and John von Neumann first conceived of computers, they did it for what would seem like an incredibly niche use. They were mostly interested in using computers to quickly solve polynomial equations or compute unwieldy integrals. They probably realized their discoveries would have other uses, but none of them probably ever conceived of digital file storage, video projection, email or the myriad of other things computers have enabled. Similarly, widespread intelligent robots could spawn a myriad of other exciting tools downstream that it’d be impossible to anticipate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robots might just be the next big world-changing tool; the tool that our descendants will look back and wonder how humans lived without. And that prospect excites me to no end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-marriage-of-bits-and-atoms&quot;&gt;A Marriage of Bits and Atoms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computer is currently arguably the greatest tool ever invented. It’s quite awe-inducing to consider just how much computers have impacted our lives in only 50 years since they were invented. Indeed, it’s quite difficult to imagine human life before computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/why-robots-pics/before_the_internet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pre-Internet&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may seem that computers can solve literally any problem, they do have an important limitation that’s been pointed out to me. Computers operate in a world of bits, but the real world operates on atoms [1]. At their core, computers are information processing machines. And while information is incredibly valuable, it is useless in of itself. The power of information -and by extension the computer – comes when it is used to manipulate the atoms of the physical world. For all their processing power and capabilities, computers cannot directly manipulate atoms, humans must constantly interpret and use computers’ information to affect the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robots seem to be the first significant bridge between the two worlds, the first marriage between bits and atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a purely abstract and perhaps insignificant point, but I think it further illustrates just how much of an impact robots could have on us. Robots will be able to both process information and act to reconfigure atoms in the physical world based on this information, much like we ourselves do. They will be able to perceive aspects of the world and thus gather and process an unprecedented amount of data, which could give us much more insight into problems that remain unsolved. They could perform basic tasks that were thought impossible to perform by anything other than a human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If computers have impacted the world this much in such a short span of time while they were limited to the world of bits, there’s no telling how much impact they could have when they begin manipulating atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-window-into-intelligence&quot;&gt;A Window into intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘What is intelligence?’ – this is arguably one of the biggest unanswered questions in human history. We can’t yet provide a precise definition of intelligence and we don’t yet actually understand how it works. Attempting to do so has been one of the largest scientific endeavors of the last century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to answer the intelligence question not only out of curiosity, but also out of utility. Intelligence has probably been humanity’s single greatest asset. Understanding it and being able to replicate intelligent behavior would be incredibly useful to us. The entire field of Artificial Intelligence (AI) is devoted to attempting to answer this question and replicate an intelligence computationally. While we’ve had significant successes so far, it doesn’t seem that a solution is in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/why-robots-pics/machine_learning.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that a significant reason for this is that we’ve been attempting to implement intelligence on disembodied computers. Personally, I’m a believer in embodied cognition – the idea that our cognition and our intelligence are significantly shaped by our bodies. If we were simply brains in vats, and did not have any method of perceiving and acting in our environments, I’m fairly certain that we would not be intelligent in the way that we currently are. Of course, this view of embodied cognition has criticisms and strong counter-arguments, but I think most people would agree that attempting to study and implement intelligence algorithms on robots can only help us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m personally very interested in the intelligence question because I think an answer will help us understand who we are fundamentally as human beings. I think an answer could have radical implications for questions ranging from religion to the origin of life. The ability to program or bestow intelligence would be an unprecedented power that could fundamentally transform our lives. I find it incredibly meaningful to contribute to this prospect. Moreover, I think that answering the intelligence question will throw light on a deeper, more fundamental question: ‘What is consciousness?’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;robots-are-really-cool&quot;&gt;Robots are &lt;em&gt;Really&lt;/em&gt; Cool&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was around 5 years old, my parents bought me the toy that everyone wanted for Christmas. It was called a RoboSapien and it was a small humanoid robot that came with a remote control that allowed you to either execute preprogrammed motions (like dancing) or finely control specific joints (like moving the hand to a specific pose to pick something up). One of my earliest memories is the raw fascination I had with this human-like toy. Here was a thing that looked human like me: it had a face and eyes and all the limbs and joints that I had. However, it couldn’t move or do anything by itself like I could. I began commanding it to do tasks like pick up a small ball and try to climb onto our sofa. I was surprised that when I tried these, I had to sit down and really think through the sequence of actions. I had to think about how much I wanted to move RoboSapien’s arms, or how far he needed to bend down – yet, if I myself were trying any of these tasks, such things would be so intuitive I wouldn’t give them a moment’s thought. I began wondering what it would take to get RoboSapien to do tasks as easily as I could. I was so fascinated that I spent days trying to think through and get RoboSapien to execute tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I could get RoboSapien to do something new, like pick up a pencil, I felt a pure rush of excitement. Here was a machine – a thing built by humans – that could pick something up or climb over something just like a human could. It felt so incredibly significant that I had just taught a machine something new. I dreamt of teaching RoboSapien to do more, like cook me a pizza or pick up a pencil and do my homework, but alas these remained out of reach. Still, every time I played with my RoboSapien, I felt a unique mixture of excitement and awe at how incredibly cool this little machine was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk has previously stated that one of the reasons he founded SpaceX was because space exploration is really cool (not his exact words). He feels that space has a unique ability to ignite human minds and make millions of people from diverse backgrounds extremely excited for the future. I think that robotics has a similar magnitude of coolness and potential to excite. I think the vision of a future where intelligent machines of multiple forms are a part of our daily lives is fundamentally exciting. And I would cite the popularity of science fiction works such as ‘Iron Man’ or ‘I Robot’ as evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, regardless of whether a vast majority of humans think robots are cool, I still very much think so. To this day, whenever I work with robots, I still feel like I did when I was a 5-year-old kid playing with his RoboSapien. I’ve not really been able to find another field that gives me such a sense of excitement and awe no matter what I work on within it. Despite the fact that current robots are incredibly complex, unwieldy, difficult-to-program things that will often fail in an incredibly esoteric manner, the prospect of working with robots still gets me out of bed every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that I’m quite biased when it comes to robots. It’s very possible that robotics could lead to a dead-end. Robots might never realize the potential I’ve talked about. They might never be even semi-intelligent or used outside of large industrial settings. Worse, they could become an active threat to humanity (a la ‘The Terminator’). There’s only one way to find out what’ll become of the field: to try it. I hope to do everything I can to ensure that we develop robots that will be a great enabler of humanity and never a threat. I acknowledge that all my efforts could be futile: whatever work I do could simply never pan out and the entire field could reveal a dead-end. While I hope this won’t happen, even if it does, then at least I’ll have gotten to play with some really cool robots for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/why-robots-pics/roomba_vet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Roomba Vet&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;A Thought Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of thought experiments. I think that a really powerful and humbling thought experiment is to imagine one’s own funeral and think about what one would like said for one’s eulogy. I’ve personally spent more time than I’d care to admit engaging in this experiment. I’ve run through hundreds of different eulogies and thought hard about what I’d like people to remember about me and my life. I’ve also run through multiple scenarios of what I could do with my life so that people would say these things and remember me fondly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One fine day, I had a dream about my funeral. Interestingly enough, the dream had nothing to do with my eulogy, but rather, what my funeral looked like. I saw a vision of a grassy field with a collection of white chairs and multiple people dressed in black. However, what stood out almost immediately were the many non-humans milling about. I saw a couple robots walking around and serving food and refreshments and greeting humans with almost flawless natural language. Another few robots were assisting some elderly people to stand up and walk wherever they pleased. There were also a few young children running around and playing tag with a small, RoboSapien-esque robot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the funeral scenarios I’ve considered, this is the scenario I like the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size: 80%&quot;&gt;Footnotes:
&lt;br /&gt; [1] I wish I could’ve come up with such a neat, beautiful metaphor, but all credit rightly goes to the amazing &lt;a href=&quot;https://mills-scofield.com/&quot;&gt;Deb Mills-Scofield&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; [2] All illustration credit here goes to &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/&quot;&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><category term="Research" /><summary type="html">Ever since my parents bought me my first robotic toy as a kid, I’ve been excited about robots. Over the years, I’ve been lucky enough to have had numerous opportunities to work with robots. I’ve played with toys, spent multiple years building Lego and heavy-metal robots for competitions, and most-recently done research with robots. So, when it came time for me to seriously consider what I want to do with the rest of my life, ‘work with robots’ was the first and natural choice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Humans, Robots And Lessons From Hri 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Humans,-Robots-and-Lessons-from-HRI-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Humans, Robots And Lessons From Hri 2019" /><published>2019-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Humans,-Robots-and-Lessons-from-HRI-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Humans,-Robots-and-Lessons-from-HRI-2019/">&lt;p&gt;Over winter break, I had the opportunity to write an extended abstract (my first first-author thing!) for an idea I’d been kicking around with some other members of my lab. We ended up submitting said abstract to VAM-HRI 2019: a workshop centered on Mixed-Reality for Human-Robot Interaction. Fortunately enough, our work got accepted (find it here!) and I had the incredible opportunity to miss a week of classes to attend Human-Robot Interaction 2019 in South Korea! This was my first ever robotics conference and what follows will be my thoughts from the conference, roughly organized as below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Major takeaways + trends from HRI 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robot companies + demos!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;major-takeaways-and-trends-from-hri-2019&quot;&gt;Major Takeaways and Trends from HRI 2019&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-the-rise-of-virtual-augmented-and-mixed-reality&quot;&gt;1. The rise of Virtual, Augmented and Mixed Reality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit that this may be my own biased opinion. After all, my primary purpose behind going to this conference was to attend the VAM (Virtual, Augmented and Mixed-Reality) workshop where I myself had authored work that heavily relied on Mixed Reality. But, I was (pleasantly) surprised to see quite a few people that weren’t just part of VAM-HRI actually use VR, AR or MR for things from robot learning to conducting experiments on social robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HRI-pics/AR_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AR Robot&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some used VR or AR for prototyping and design, and many others used it for experiments. Of particular interest was the fact that three different works attempted to use VAM technologies to facilitate robot Learning from Demonstration (LfD). Two of these focused on methods to build large-scale VR simulations of environments and tasks to collect a very large amount of training data from users via the internet.  This idea has been around for a while (there has even been some work from our lab about it!) but it was encouraging to see other people attempting to take it forward. Indeed, it would be incredible if we could have some sort of game where players could record themselves doing common tasks and we could then use these recordings to train a robot (in simulation) to do the same tasks (and hopefully eventually do them in real life!). The third LfD work was unique in that it proposed to use Mixed Reality holograms to provide constraints on demonstrations being collected. This was an incredibly fascinating (and apt!) use of MR for robot learning and I ended up tracking down the authors and attempting to pick their brains on how they’d come up with this idea and what they planned to do with it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HRI-pics/AR_Prezi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AR Prezi&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall however, there were many more works that used VR, AR or MR than I’d expected. Earlier this year, some (smarter) lab members made me have the key realization that VR, AR and MR could act like new communication modalities between humans and robots. It was interesting and very exciting to see others realize this too and use these modalities in significant and unique ways!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-ethics-and-accountability&quot;&gt;2. Ethics and Accountability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably stuck with me because of how surprised I was to hear about it. As a (still-developing) robotics researcher, I’m used to hearing technical computer science or engineering fueled discussions. So hearing someone raise ethical concerns and begin talking about public policy and law while describing human-robot experiments was surprising to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before attending the conference, I didn’t think ethics or accountability were major problems that deserved attention – primarily because robots aren’t sufficiently advanced to be significantly dangerous yet. ‘We can figure this out after we have intelligent and generally-capable robots’ – I thought. I’m really glad multiple people have devoted more thought to this issue than I had. People raised important issues regarding self-driving cars and drones and pointed out that these inventions are already here and are already being used to do &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-46827542&quot;&gt;questionable things&lt;/a&gt;. At one point, there was an interesting debate about the difference between a robot and a pencil. Is a robot only a tool who’s accountability lies solely with the wielder? Or – given these are intelligent, decision-making agents – are the programmers or makers accountable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While people debated back and forth on what the legal and ethical status of robots should be, most concurred that we as researchers need to be thinking about these problems as we build our robots and not after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-robots-as-caregivers&quot;&gt;3. Robots as caregivers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the conference, I’d been tangentially aware that people were thinking about using robots to care for seniors, patients and children. What I didn’t know was just how many people were working on this and how serious they were about it. And it turns out there are quite a lot of people that are very serious about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There turned out to be two entire sessions of the conference dedicated to caregiving robots: “Robots in care” and “Robots engaging children”. I was consistently surprised by the kind of challenges people were solving for these domains; the conference’s best paper ended up being about the best way for a robot to feed a human – something I’d never even considered was a challenging technical problem (and one that had an interesting and quite innovative solution at that!). There were quite a few people that conducted large-scale studies on what users would want from a robot caregiver, and while results differed, the common fact was that almost every user wants a caregiving robot. This was incredibly interesting because I’m used to people being afraid that robots will steal their jobs; but here is a legitimate, real-world domain where people overwhelmingly want robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;robot-companies--demos&quot;&gt;Robot companies + demos!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the coolest things I got to see at the conference was all the companies and demos they’d brought. There were a lot, but I only got to visit and take pictures of a few, which I’ll try to summarize them (with pictures!) below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-simulated-robot-arm-for-cad&quot;&gt;A simulated robot arm for CAD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I unfortunately forgot this company’s name – but their demo was one of the coolest I’ve seen. They had a physical robotic arm with a simulation where you could create virtual objects but feel them for real using the physical arm. Unfortunately, we were informed we’d have to ask for a quote if we’d like to own one…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HRI-pics/CAD_arm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CAD Arm demo&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;robotis&quot;&gt;Robotis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a company that made various small robots for education or research. They’re intended to be cheap so the average school or small research lab could buy them. Despite this, they were pretty cool and had impressive demos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HRI-pics/robotis_hands.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robotis hands&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HRI-pics/classification.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robotic Classifier&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;furhat-robotics&quot;&gt;Furhat Robotics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was by far the most interesting company I saw and I ended up talking to them for quite a while. It’s difficult to describe their product well – so I’ll just show you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HRI-pics/furhat.png&quot; alt=&quot;Furhat Robotics&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the robot is a voice assistant with a reconfigurable face. I was shown a demo where the face and voice were quickly shifted between popular celebrities (so I technically got to meet Obama and Arnold Schwarzenegger) and it was pretty cool (although sometimes difficult to identify the celebrities’ faces).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The robot can track people with a camera, follow their face or voice and hold a conversation (albeit with somewhat weird lip movement and facial expressions). I tried to test the tracking and it was quite impressive, especially given this was in a large hall with lots of background noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most interesting thing about the company though was their customers. There’s a lot of what you might expect: airports or companies wanting something to man the information desk 24/7. But there’s also apparently been a steady demand from HR departments at some large companies. Why? Because Furhat robots can conduct HR training programmes in a completely unbiased way. These robots are designed to interact and respond to language without a single care for factors like age, sex or ethnicity – which is apparently a big draw for companies hoping to institute fairer training programmes and policies. This was a pretty surprising and interesting use-case for social robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;overall-thoughts&quot;&gt;Overall Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this conference was probably one of the best things I’ve done in recent times. I got to meet and interact with so many PhD students doing exciting work and also a few amazing professors (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bradhayes.info/&quot;&gt;Brad Hayes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://eecs.oregonstate.edu/people/knight-heather&quot;&gt;Heather Knight&lt;/a&gt;). I even got to see some superstars that I’d only ever read about like &lt;a href=&quot;https://goodrobot.ai/&quot;&gt;Sidd Srinivasa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~anca/&quot;&gt;Anca Dragan&lt;/a&gt; (it felt like spotting celebrities!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most significant thing was simply getting to experience what a real large robotics conference is like. Two things that stood out were how large and international the robotics and intelligence community is. It was quite shocking to realize that I was attending a conference on a specific sub-field of robotics (human-robot interaction) and there were more than 1000 other attendees from all around the world. The fact that so many intelligent people from so many backgrounds are putting their careers into the field is incredibly heartening and inspiring. I left Korea more convinced than ever that I want to spend my life working with robots.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Conference" /><summary type="html">Over winter break, I had the opportunity to write an extended abstract (my first first-author thing!) for an idea I’d been kicking around with some other members of my lab. We ended up submitting said abstract to VAM-HRI 2019: a workshop centered on Mixed-Reality for Human-Robot Interaction. Fortunately enough, our work got accepted (find it here!) and I had the incredible opportunity to miss a week of classes to attend Human-Robot Interaction 2019 in South Korea! This was my first ever robotics conference and what follows will be my thoughts from the conference, roughly organized as below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">More Than A 45: A Reflection On My Time In High School</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/More-than-a-45-a-reflection-on-my-time-in-High-School/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More Than A 45: A Reflection On My Time In High School" /><published>2017-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/More-than-a-45:-a-reflection-on-my-time-in-High-School</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/More-than-a-45-a-reflection-on-my-time-in-High-School/">&lt;p&gt;So this post is actually an article I wrote for my school’s student newsletter. I was asked to submit this some time before my TA internship at my school ended and I think it really encompasses my experience and views toward the IB. I’ve put it here in the hopes that it might be useful to student coming into the IB or trying to decide on their IB school. I hope you guys have as fulfilling an experience as I did 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the IB’s full of anything, it’s definitely numbers (especially if you take Math HL). There’s numbers everywhere: 3 HL’s and 3 SL’s, 120 hours of teaching, 4000 word EE, 1600 word TOK essay, 9 hours of class every-day, 15 papers of about 70 marks each; and of course, the final score out of 45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing I’ve noticed both during and after the IB is that people seem to only care about these numbers. How many words was your EE? How much did you get in TOK? What was your final number of CAS hours? And of course, the most common: What was your final score? These are the most frequently-asked questions I’ve got. The last one is asked particularly often; so much so that I’ve now become “the guy who got 45” to most people, as if I’m some disembodied walking number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started the IB DP, I was obsessed with the numbers like all the aforementioned people. But looking back now, I realize IB wasn’t just a set of numbers to me. I think I speak for almost-all IB graduates when I say that: it’s about more than just numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I got a 45: a perfect score. But that doesn’t even begin to quantify my IB experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/more-than-45-pics/tips_2016.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My IB Class&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      A picture of everyone from my graduating IB Class

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined the IB, I was scared to stand-up and talk to a class of my peers. But now, I teach confidently in front of people I’ve never met before. I’ve even given a speech to the whole school. I’ve made friends with previous strangers and attempted to understand their worldviews. 45 doesn’t quantify that humongous growth in my confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I began IB, I was so confused about who I was, who I wanted to be and what I wanted to do with my life. Now, I’ve come to understand a few things: I’m driven, I’m a hopeless dreamer and I want to change the world as an Engineer. (I’m also a proud nerd!) That’s at least a start; but 45 doesn’t quantify that transformative self-discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45 cannot represent the friends I’ve made and all the amazing discussions I’ve shared. It cannot begin to represent the projects I’ve done, the successes I’ve had and the failures I’ve endured in this two-year roller-coaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45 does not fathom the heart-wrenching grief I felt when my dear Physics Teacher and EE Supervisor, Mr. Venkat, passed away of cancer. 45 says nothing of the promise I made to his memory, of the iron determination that gripped me to fulfill my promise and be Venkat Sir’s first student to achieve a perfect score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45 doesn’t quantify what I felt when I got my results and cried with joy because I’d somehow fulfilled that impossible promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IB is about so much more than just numbers. It’s the first time most students (myself included) get a taste of freedom; freedom to pursue our own ideas and experiments and do whatever we fancy with time. And that can be scary, but it’s also exhilarating because we’re finally getting a taste of the real-world and all the responsibility that comes with it. To me, IB was about growing up, about understanding and learning more and becoming a better person. And I can honestly say that it was probably the best two years of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve been asked by a lot of people “Why do you still come to school?”. They seem so puzzled, so absolutely flabbergasted. I usually smile at that question, because I realize that everyone who asks it still doesn’t understand. They still think IB and school is all about numbers and that I’m done now because I got a 45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t show up for numbers. I show up to learn more about the subjects and myself, to help others, to be in an environment I love with vibrant and amazing people and to interact with teachers who’ve become like my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I show up for everything else; everything mere numbers can’t hope to measure.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nishanth J. Kumar</name><email>nishanth.kumar20@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Meditations" /><category term="IB" /><summary type="html">So this post is actually an article I wrote for my school’s student newsletter. I was asked to submit this some time before my TA internship at my school ended and I think it really encompasses my experience and views toward the IB. I’ve put it here in the hopes that it might be useful to student coming into the IB or trying to decide on their IB school. I hope you guys have as fulfilling an experience as I did 🙂</summary></entry></feed>